<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A co[m]parison betwene the olde learnynge [and] the newe translated out of latin in Englysh by Wylliam Turner.</title>
            <author>Rhegius, Urbanus, 1489-1541.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1537</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104610</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840343</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4840</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10570)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4840)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 141:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A co[m]parison betwene the olde learnynge [and] the newe translated out of latin in Englysh by Wylliam Turner.</title>
                  <author>Rhegius, Urbanus, 1489-1541.</author>
                  <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By me James Nicolso[n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Prynted in Sowthwarke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1537.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Urbanus Rhegius's 'Novae doctrinae ad veterem collatio'.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G [par.]⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Early printed works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4840:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4840:1"/>
            <p>A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon betwene the Olde lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge &amp; the Newe,</p>
            <p>¶ Tranſlated out of latin in Englyſh by Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iam Turner.</p>
            <p>Prynted in Sowthwarke by me Iames Nicolſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Anno. 1537.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:4840:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The contentes of this boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Of the ſacramentes.</item>
               <item>Of penaunce.</item>
               <item>Of confeſſion.</item>
               <item>Of ſatiſfaccyon.</item>
               <item>Of frewyll.</item>
               <item>Of fayth and workes.</item>
               <item>Of merites.</item>
               <item>Of ſynne.</item>
               <item>Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhippynge of ſayntes.</item>
               <item>Of the ſupper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde.</item>
               <item>Of the choyſe of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</item>
               <item>Of faſtynge.</item>
               <item>Of the difference of dayes.</item>
               <item>Of prayer.</item>
               <item>Of vowes.</item>
               <item>Of counſelles.</item>
               <item>Of matrimony.</item>
               <item>Of biſſhoppes.</item>
               <item>Of ceremonies.</item>
               <item>Of mans traditions.</item>
               <item>Of councels &amp; lawes made by a multitude of biſſhoppes gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>¶ To the reader.</head>
            <l>Some ther be that do defye</l>
            <l>All that is newe, and euer do crye</l>
            <l>The olde is better, awaye with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new</l>
            <l>Becauſe it is falſe, and the olde is true:</l>
            <l>Let them this boke reade and beholde</l>
            <l>For it preferreth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> learnyng moſt olde.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4840:2"/>
            <head>¶ Vrbanus Regius to a certayne frende of his, wyſheth <hi>CHRIST</hi> oure ryghteouſneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han our ſaueour in the fyrſt of Marke had caſte out of a man an vncleane ſprete, the Iewes were aſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge: what new learnynge is this? It was thought new to thoſe wretches for lacke of knowlege of ſcripture: which of all thynges was oldeſt, that is to ſaye the Goſpell, the which was longe tofore promyſed by the prophetes in the ſcripture, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God Ieſu Chriſt. The ſame thynge was ſayd to Paul, whan he preached Chriſt at Athene: they toke him &amp; led hym to Marcis ſtrete, ſayenge: May we not knowe what new learnyng this is, that ye teach? for ye brynge in to our eares new thynges. Was the teachynge of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles (I praye you) ſtrayght waye new, becauſe it was thought new to the proude gentyles ſwellynge and bounde with theyr carnall and fleſhly wyſedome? Euen ſuche lyke thinges in theſe later dayes, do they al ſuffer: which teach purely the Goſpel of the
<pb facs="tcp:4840:3"/>
gracyous fauour and glory of God. Which do not abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of euerlaſtynge truth for auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage: but as it were of ſyncerneſſe, but as it were of god, ſo ſpeak we by Chriſt in the ſyght of God. This is the new doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine (ſaye our aduerſaries) lately deuyſed &amp; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnyſhed in the ſhoppes or workhouſes of heretikes. Let vs abyde ſtyl in our old fayth Let the holyneſſe of our fathers, the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, the conſent of the longe tyme &amp; ſo many ages, holde vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayes of our fathers. Let the heretikes go &amp; ſhake theyr eares, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr new learnynge, which ſpronge and roſe vp of late. Thoſe thynges which we teach came not all from Chriſte and the Apoſtles by wrytynge, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they came by a faythfull reuelacyon, &amp; ſhewynge vnto vs. To whom I wyll an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere none otherwyſe then Chriſt anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Saduces: Ye erre (ſayeth he) and ar ignoraunt in the ſcripture. And wolde to God that I myghte purchace and obtayne ſo much equyte of a braynleſſe kynde of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as one heythen man ſheweth to another: that is, yf they wolde fyrſt heare the cauſe or matter, and then afterwarde (yf it pleaſe them) condemne hym that is accuſed. Now they condemne innocentes without ony
<pb facs="tcp:4840:3"/>
hearynge of theyr cauſe. And they crye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs which defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge but galowes, ropes, and fyre, not witeſafyng vs the leeſt corner of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke church. In ſo much that I wonder of what ſprete they be of. For that gentle and pleaſaunt ſprete of Chriſt, the which fedeth the myſticall body, ſeketh for the health and not for the deſtruccyon of them that erre. Charite the frute of the holy gooſt (as the apoſtell ſayeth) doth thynke none euell, but is glad and reioyceth with the trueth, bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all thynges, truſteth all thynges. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely they that ſet aſyde the blynde iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the affeccyon, and loke earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the matter, iudge otherwyſe of vs. For the olde au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient fathers dyd neuer knowe or heare tell, of the mooſt parte of thoſe thynges, whiche oure condemners do teache: then ye maye be ſure that theyr lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge ought not to be rekened for olde lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge and apoſtolicall. Furthermore not euery thynge that the olde fathers wrote ſauoureth of the ſyncerneſſe and pureneſſe of the ſprete of the Apoſtles. Certayne thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges which were deuiſed with in theſe foure hundreth yeares, yee rather euen of late haue bene receaued by and by of them, as
<pb facs="tcp:4840:4"/>
ſoone as they were made, namely this is theyr learnynge and ſo olde that they deſyre for this, that the Goſpell almooſt ſhulde be caſt awaye, and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted as a new teachynge and learnynge. Therfore I wolde that they ſhulde knowe and vnderſtande that we do teache and preache the olde and the trewe heauenly doctryne of the ſprete: that is the goſpell of god. The greate myſtery of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and godlyneſſe that god was declared in the fleſhe, was iuſtified in ſprete, ſene of the angelles, preached to the gentyles, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence was geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him in the worlde, &amp; was receaued in to glory. What ſaye you be theſe newes: God dyd predeſtinate vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght choſe and purches vs to be his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, by Chriſte Ieſus in his owne ſelfe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the pleaſure of his wyl, that the glory of the grace of God myght be prayſed, whereby he made vs welbeloued, thorowe his welbeloud, by whome we haue rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorowe his bloude, forgeueneſſe of ſynnes accordyng to the ryches of his grace: This was the fathers counſell vpon vs, before the begynnyng of the worlde, that he ſhuld ſaue vs, and calle vs with an holy vocacion, not accordyng to our workes, but accordyng to his purpoſe and grace, whiche is geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:4840:4"/>
vs thorowe Ieſus Chriſt before the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting times, but it is opened and declared nowe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appearing of our ſaueour Chriſt which put deathe away and hathe thorowe the goſpel brought forthe the lyfe into lyght and mortalite. The which thyng ſeyng that it was promyſed ſo longe ago by the prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of the holy gooſte and nowe publiſhed thorowe al the coaſtes of the worlde, howe dare they for ſhame call it newe learnyng? Ceaſſe you wycked men and ſtaunche your blaſphemyes geue glory and prayſe with vs vnto god: and enbrace &amp; loue (as ye ought to do) the myſteries of the truthe with deuoute myndes, lefte ye be in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>durate and made harde harted of god, with the reprobate and caſtawayes: the which be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue not the truth, but alowe vnryghtuouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe. The are is layed at the roote of the trees. Wherfore I doynge the offyce of a chriſten brother, haue made a comparyſon betwene the newe learnynge and the olde, whereby deare brother thou maye eaſely knowe whether we are called worthely or vnworthely the preachers of new learnyng. For ſo dyd they call vs of late, ſcornynge and of a contempte, and you deſyred of
<pb facs="tcp:4840:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
me to know what I thought beſt to anſwer to theſe braynles and madde fellowes. The which thynge ſeynge that it can not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in an epyſtell: I thought it beſte to beſtow a few houres in thys matter, in theſe dayes called faſtyngam, in latyn carnis priuium, whiche hath the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> takyng awaye of fleſhe. In the which dayes after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of the gentyles and heythen men, they vſe vncomly playes and games. Take in good worth the labour of your frende. Fare ye well, and to God for me a ſynner.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. The new learyng.</head>
                  <p>It is ynough and ſuffycient to receaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramentes effectually and with frute to haue no ſtoppe nor let of deadly ſynne: And ther is not requyred in a man a good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion within hym whiche receaueth them, whereby of a congruence or of worthynes he maye deſerue grace: for the ſacramentes brynge grace with them of the worke that is wrought by them, or by the worke it ſelf: that is to ſaye bycauſe the worke is ſhewed &amp; myniſtred as a ſygne or a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Thys ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſter of ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in the .iiii. boke in the fyrſt diſtinction. By the doctores.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4840:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>The goſpel witneſſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be ſaued not by an holy ſygne, but thorow fayth. Gene. xv. Abraham gaue credence &amp; beleued God and that was rekened to hym for ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe. Rom. iiii. Rom. x. Yf a man beleue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the harte he ſhalbe made ryghteous. He ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth not: that with the body an holy ſygne is taken vnto ryghteouſneſſe. Alſo Abacuc. ii. and Roma. the fyrſt. The iuſte ſhal lyue by his fayth. He ſayeth not: He ſhal lyue by the ſacramentes. It foloweth therfore after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde learnynge, that fayth is neceſſary to be had in hym that receaueth the ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes with frute.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of penaunce the new learnynge.</head>
                  <p>A mans wyll onely naturally (doynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyeth in hym) maye diſpoſe it ſelfe to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauynge of grace, by an acte confirmable vnto ryght reaſon, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is morally good Alſo a mans wyll in puttynge awaye a ſtop or let, that is the purpoſe of deadly ſinne, of a good motion drawen out of frewyll, may deſerue the fyrſt grace of a congruence. In the ſeconde boke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſter of ſentence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxv. diſtinction. What meaneth this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:4840:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
els, but that (as Pelagius ſayeth) the begynnyng of our iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of our ſelues, and the ende of makyng perfect com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth of God? Then myght a man by hys owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth begynne penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which they call co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trycion: as though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnyng of it were in vs. Thys learnyng maketh ypocry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, &amp; maynteyneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryde of the olde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learninge.</head>
                  <p>In the tenth chap. of zachary it is wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I wyll conuerte them becauſe I wyll haue mercy vpon them Trenoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v. Conuerte vs Lorde to the, and we ſhalbe conuerted. Ihon xv. Without me ye can do nothyng. Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſ. ii. God worketh the wyll .ii. Corinth. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iii. Chapter. Euery good thought is of God. Roma. xi. Yf it be of workes, then is it not of grace .ii. Timothe the .iii. Chapt. Yf God at ony tyme wyll geue them repentaunce. &amp;c. Therfore after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde learnyng repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is the gyfte of God, the which grace that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyeth, worketh, and not the power which draweth oute frewyll. Before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme that a man haue grace, nother his thought nor his wyl is good: nother hath he ony good work, but al is ſyn: for as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tre is, ſuch is his frute. The perſone is a ſynner, &amp; alſo fleſhe: then,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:6"/>
what other thynge can it ſauour, wyn, and worke but fleſhly thynges. Thys doctryne maketh men lowly and beateth downe the pryde and arrogancye of the olde Adam.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of confeſſion, the new learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Who ſo euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to the yeares of diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crecyon, at the leaſt once in the yeare, he is bounde to confeſſe all his ſynnes, both open and ſecrete: with all theyr circumſtaunces to his curate, or els he is not a chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the biſhop hath authoryte, to reſerue, &amp; kepe onely to hym ſelf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forgeueneſſe of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſynnes: by the reaſon af theyr greate enormyte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which a ſimple preſt cannot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyle, but in the poynt of death, ſo do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new fellowes ſaye. As in the canon lawe, Cap. Omnis vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſexus. &amp;c. and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mayſter of ſentence aboute the .xvii. diſtinction.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>In the .xxxi. Pſalme: I haue ſayde I wyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe agaynſt me myne vnryghteouſneſſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, &amp; thou haſte forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyneſſe of my ſynne. Beholde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophete doth confeſſe hym to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord: &amp; he getteth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geueneſſe of al his ſinnes. Luc. xviii. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>can ſayeth: be mercyful to me a ſinner, &amp; he goeth home iuſtified into his houſe. Where is here ony rehearſyng, of circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, &amp; of
<pb facs="tcp:4840:7"/>
hydde ſynnes, in the preſtes eare. Luce. vii. the ſynful woman ſpeaketh nothynge, but wepeth and falleth lowly downe at the fete of Ieſus, and ſhe had by &amp; by forgeueneſſe of hir ſynnes, &amp; herd ſayd vnto her: Departe in peace. Mathew the .iii. Ieruſalem and al Iewry and all the contry nexte to the flode Iordane, goeth forth to Ihon, and they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe theyr ſynnes: namely in a general con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion. For they graunted themſelues to be ſynners: in as muche as they axed bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, a ſygne of repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yet for al that ye heare of no rehearſall of ſynnes. We reade in the actes that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thynge was done at Epheſus at the preachynge of the Apoſtell: yet for all that we ſe in no place theſe wordes, a peculiar or proper preſte: al hyd ſynnes, all circumſtaunces, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In the fyrſt of Ihon the .i. chapter we haue a confeſſion which is of goddes lawe, by the which we confeſſe our fautes lowly to God the knower of mens hartes: and he is faythful &amp; ryghteous to forgeue vs them For he geueth grace to lowly perſones, and reſyſteth proude men .i. Pet. v. Where as true penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is, truly there is alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the true frute of penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. We do not vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terly forſake auricular or eare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but
<pb facs="tcp:4840:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> addycions of mans tradycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are parted and ſondered from holſom doctryne, as chaf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe is from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corne. It is an holſom doctryne and accordynge to goddes lawe, to requyre the lawe of the mouthe of a preſte, and to learne of the byſſhop the waye of the Lorde. Malachi. ii. Agge. ii. .i. Timot. iii. Titu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. Therfore I wolde not that the order of the church ſhuld be broken, which is .i. Corin. xii where the Apoſtell after that he had made mencyon of the myſtical body, ſheweth that Chriſt ſet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church or congregacion, fyrſt Apoſtels, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prophetes or preachers thyrd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly teachers, why ſhulde teachers be in the churche? Namely for thys entent, that they hauyng the faſhion and the form of holſome wordes ſhuld teache the churche thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which be neceſſary for mans ſaluation: and reſiſte with the ſwearde of the ſpryte, the enemyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth &amp; all vngodlyneſſe: and that they might preache y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde bothe openly and preuely, that they be feruent in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, that they rebuke, reproue, and exorte with all gentelneſſe and learnyng .ii. Timoth. iiii. Let them knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face and countenance of theyr floke, and to be ſhorte, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be full of thoſe wertues, the which god requireth. Ezechiel. xxxiiii. of the
<pb facs="tcp:4840:8"/>
watcheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ouerſeers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Iſrael: Yf we perceaue not and be ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ony thynge that pertayneth vnto a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lyuyng, and it is not playnely taught in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> open ſermon, we muſt go to the curate, to-heare of hys mouth the iudgementes and teſtimonyes of the Lorde. Yf ony doute aryſe in oure conſciences, whome ought we rather to go to, and axe counſell, then of the hyrdman of our ſoules? Farthermore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be faynte harted or haue no corage and are vexed with te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacions: we maye not deſpyſe the remedye that god ordened. Thou haſt Gods worde. Math. xviii. Where as .ii. or .iii. &amp;c. And Ihon. xx. Whoſe ſynnes ye ſhal remyt. &amp;c. Whome wold not theſe fatherly promyſes prouoke and alure to confeſſion? where as the conſcience is lyfted vp and ſtabliſſhed not by mans worde, but by god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, ſpoken by mans mouth. But theſe be mans addicions to bynde a mans conſcience with a law, and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell hym to confeſſe all hys ſynnes with all theyr circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces at a certayne tyme, to hys owne preſte or curate whatſoeuer he be: whereby mens conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces be marked with an whote yron. For he that is not confeſſed after the maner that is preſcrybed in the confeſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:8"/>
ether by the reaſon of ignoraunce, or of a frayle memory or ſhamefaſtneſſe (yee though he be aſhamed and repent hym of hys euell lyfe with all hys harte) yet for all that as longe as he lyueth he beareth about wyth hym an vnquyet conſcience, and full of diſpayre. And yf a man take a lyttell diligence, or haue a good memory, or wryte hys ſynnes in a pece of paper, and poureth oute into a frears eare, that can not well heare all the fylthyneſſe of hys vncleane lyuynge. good Lorde how glad is he? that not onely he hath ſatiſfiſed the law: but becauſe alſo that he hath taken of hys ſhulders a burthen heuyer then Ethna the hyl that always burneth. Then as who ſay, he hath deſerued forgeueneſſe of hys ſyn with thys troubleſome worke, he ſtandeth in his owne conceate, which wold haue dyſpay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, yf he had not rehearſed hys ſynnes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thys maner. Let the byſſhoppes appoint learned men to heare confeſſyons, and not blockheades: &amp; then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people ſhall come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes by heapes and ſwarmes. The whiche thynge whyle they do it not, lette them blame them ſelues, and not vs, yf the people ſet lytle by theyr curates. Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more as concernyng the reſeruyng,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:9"/>
and kepyng behynde of certayn cauſes and chaunces, let the head rulers in the church tel a cauſe why they do differ and abhorre ſo greatly the Apoſtles rytes and teachynges. A preſte or an elder &amp; a biſhop with Paull, be all one. The ſcripture maketh no ſuch difference, of miniſters, in the laboure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell. Whan the Lord ſent forth hys diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, he gaue them lyke power, ſayng: Go into all the world and preach the goſpel to euery creature: he that ſhal beleue and be baptyſed ſhalbe ſaued. Marke. xvi. Iohn. xx. he ſayth vnto them: Take ye the holy gooſt, &amp; whoſoeuer ſynnes ye forgeue, they ſhalbe forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Where is here ony dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, betwene a biſſhop &amp; a ſymple preſte? Is it harde to knowe what thys be to ſaye: Whoſe ſynnes ye remyt they ſhalbe remyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? Thys ys the doctrine of Chriſte and hys Aoſtels.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of ſatiſfaction. The new learnyng.</head>
                  <p>A certayn ſatiſfaccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to be enioyned to hym that is confeſſed for hys ſynnes that be paſt, accordyng to the quantite or qualite of the ſynnes, that he may content and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the ryghteouſneſſe of God. Thys hath the .xvii. and .xviii. diſtinction of the fourth
<pb facs="tcp:4840:9"/>
boke. By this doctrine the grace of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is darkened, ouerſhadowed, and defaced, and mans workes enhaunced to the mooſt hye iniury of Chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Eſay the .liii. Chapter. He is broken for oure wyckedneſſes. The father hath layed on his necke all our iniquityes and wycked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes. I haue ſmytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym for the myſchefe of my people. Here thou mayeſt ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte dyd ſatiſfaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſynnes of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Alſo .i. Pet. ii. He bare our ſynnes in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, on the croſſe, that we ſhuld be delyuered from ſynne, &amp; ſhuld lyue in ryghteouſneſſe, by whoſe ſtrypes we are healed. Alſo in the fyrſt epiſtle to the Corinthians the .i. chap. Chriſt is our ryghteouſneſſe and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Ioh in the .x. Chapter. Chriſt ſpent hys lyfe for hys ſhepe. Rom. the .v. Chap. We be brought in fauoure with the father, by the death of Chriſt, and not by our ſatiſfaccyon The ſame we haue alſo Ephe. the .i. And Colloſſenſes .i. &amp; .ii. Chriſt toke away the ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligacyon or handwrytynge, whiche was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> decrees, &amp; he faſtened it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe .i. Ioh. i. The bloud of Chriſt clenſeth &amp; pourgeth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſynne. He ſayeth not
<pb facs="tcp:4840:10"/>
our ſatiſfaccion doth pourge vs. Now haue we proued by theſe places y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> onyly the death of Chriſt is our full ſatiſfaccyon for the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of al the world, and not our fylthy rygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Let vs than cal thoſe ſcourges or puniſhmentes which our louynge father ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs, or we take our ſelues (preuentyng the hande of God) correccyon, ſtrokes and ſuch other names as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture vſeth. This worde ſatiſfaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a proude worde and ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to al chriſten eares, that heare ſomtime the ſounde of this ſayenge of S. Luke in the xv. Chap. Whan we haue done all thynges which be commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto vs, yet we maye ſaye that we be vnprofytable ſeruauntes.</p>
                  <p>Let claye &amp; aſſhes be aſhamed of this proud worde ſatiſfaccyon for ſynne. Shame be vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs and ryghteouſneſſe vnto God. Yf we with our workes and correccyons do make amendes or ſatiffaccyon for our ſynnes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt dyed in vayne. And by this doctrine the grace that bryngeth vs in the fauour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, is magnifyed by the bloude of Ieſus, and mans worke is lytell ſet by, to the moſt worthy prayſe of Chriſtes paſſyon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of fre wyll. The new learnynge.</head>
                  <p>A man hath fre wyll &amp; choyſe not only
<pb facs="tcp:4840:10"/>
in the ſtate of innocency, but alſo of his fall and ſynne: And it is of ſo great vertue, that he doynge that lyeth in hym, may remoue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtoppe and hynderaunce of grace, &amp; diſpoſe hymſelfe to grace that iuſtifyeth. And leſt a carnall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, proud ynough of hymſelfe, ſhuld wante noryſhynge for hys arrogancy, they go aboute to ſtrengthen and confirme this doctrine with ſcriptures falſely vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Eccleſiaſticus in the .xv. (ſaye theye) ſayeth and proueth fre wyll, where as God is ſayd to haue left a man in the power of his own counſell, and to haue geuen hym commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which (yf he do kepe) they ſhuld kepe and ſaue him. And to this purpoſe they ſwepe &amp; gather together, what ſo euer lawe or monition is ony where in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture. As who ſay we myght gather wel after this maner: God hath commaunded that we ſhuld do this, he hath apoynted the condycy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons of lyfe, he threatneth payne to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that breake them: ergo it is in oure power to do that ſame? wote ye wel here is a ſure argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? much lyke vnto this, the mayſter byd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t go an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth myles on one day: ergo he may go an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth myles on a daye. Although I ſe many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of great repu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almoſt promyſyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory
<pb facs="tcp:4840:11"/>
in the defendyng of frewyl, with this ſhorte argument. Whan in the meane ſeaſon they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder not how lytle this doctrine maketh for the glory of Chriſt which before al thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges oughte to be ſoughte. Is it not a great ſklaunder of the true learnynge, to teach af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter this wyſe: Grace geuen frely, or the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall influence with the vnderſtandynge, that vnderſtandeth or directeth aryght, and the wyll confirmably wyllyng, are ynough to deſerue the fyrſt grace, whiche maketh a man fyrſt to come in fauour? Who wolde haue loked for ſo muche lyfe and health in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man that was left halfe dead of the theues, Luce. x. that although he could not heal him ſelfe, yet he myght go in to the potycaryes ſhoppe, nedynge no horſe, myght ſhewe hys grefe, bye ſalues &amp; pay for them whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had done? Go to I am content let them teach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtificacyon can not be by our ſtrength, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iuſtifieth: yet they teach that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnynge of penaunce is in vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they geue vnto vs the preparynge vnto grace, doynge as muche as lyeth in vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye deſerue of a ſymlyneſſe the fyrſt grace by a good mocyon drawen out of the fredome of the wyll. Is not this to geue the fyrſte good motion to nature? Moreouer, they ſaye:
<pb facs="tcp:4840:11"/>
That a man by his naturall ſtrength, may fulfyll goddes commaundementes, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the acte, although not accordynge to the intent of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that is god. Yf that be true, it is in a ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners power to amende or to continue in ſynne. Yf nature maye do ſo muche, what nede haue we of grace? Whan ſymple men heare thoſe thynges whan ſhall they at ony tyme learne Chriſt truely? whan wyl they geue thankes for the vnſpeakeable benefyte of theyr rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption? A lytell thynge holdeth me, but I laye on theſe teachers the ſayeng of ſaynt Peter: They denye the Lorde that bought them, and they make marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyſe, of the people of God, with theyr fained wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des. Whan dyd Chriſt or the Apoſtles euer ſpeake after this maner: The merite of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruence, the meryte of worthyneſſe, to do that lyeth in hym, fre wyll, the productiue vertue of fre wyl? Thou chriſten man flye theſe ſayenges as the peſtilent blaſt of the crafty ſerpent, where with he maketh oure nature (whiche is proude already) to ſwell agaynſt God. Thou haſte (good reader) a tayſte of the ſcoolemens learnynge of fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyll, the whiche hangeth nothynge toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For whan they be charged wyth ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:12"/>
in the deſpite of the Pelagians they wyll be thought fauourers of grace, ſomty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with a maruaylous euaſyon preferryng a ſpecyall helpe of God, before mans wyll both in wyllynge and in workynge. And a lytell after they leape backe agayne to the excellent gyftes of theyr nature, leſt they ſhulde be thought to fauoure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Manichees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Romano. the .xiiii. Chapter. What ſo euer is not of fayth, that is ſynne. Then that good motion of fre wyll before grace that iuſtifyeth is ſynne. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what madnes is it to wyll, to deſerue grace by ſynne? Or what lyberte is it, whan a man can not do well of hymſelfe but only euel? what health is that, to haue power to fal and not to ryſe or ſtande without the helpe of an other? the ſeconde to the Corinthians the thyrde chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. Our ſufficiency or ableneſſe to do good is of God. Roma. the thyrde Chap. Fayth iuſtifyeth. Before fayth a man is a ſynner and euell, then how can he haue a good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of hymſelfe, whom fayth hath not ſtea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vp? how can a thorne tre brynge forth a grape. Ioh. viii. Euery man that doth ſynne is the ſeruaunt of ſynne .ii. Petri. ii. A man is brought in bondage vnto hym, of whome
<pb facs="tcp:4840:12"/>
he is ouercome. Ephe. ii. By nature we be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wrath Ge. vi. We be fleſh, Io. iii. Excepte that we be borne agayne .i. Corin. ii. A carnall man perceaueth not thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges which be of the ſprete of God. Then how can the ſeruaunt of ſynne, the ſonne of wrath, fleſhe, a carnall man: before he be regenerate, haue mexe naturall power &amp; good motions of hymſelfe? Can an euell tre brynge forth good frute? Excepte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be regenerate with the grace of Chriſt? (ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge to the ymage of the earthy Adam) we beare no goodneſſe. Seynge that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt doth expreſſely and vehemently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that we be not only prone and ready to euell: but alſo euel in dede. Farthermore the Lord maketh lawes, but (before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou bryng in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Therfore we may: or els wherfore haue we ſo many preceptes &amp; threatenynges?) learne of Paul Roma. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iii. Chap. that the lawe is the knowledge of ſynne and not the auctor of ryghteouſneſſe The lawe is ſpirituall &amp; we be carnal ſolde vnder ſynne, Rom. vii. Therfore thou muſt be ſpirituall that thou maye kepe the lawe, which is not in thy power, but it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God: Wherfore thou maye learne of the lawe, to knowe thy myſery, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which after y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4840:13"/>
haſte knowen, thou arte compelled to go to Chriſte the perfeccyon and the fulfyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of the lawe. The lawe iuſtifyeth the not, but it declareth to thy ſhame, howe farre thou arte from the dew clenneſſe of lyfe by thyne owne faute. Therfore thou mayeſt not thynke thus with thy ſelfe: I haue a good lawe, what nedeth more, but my laboure and dylygence? I knowe good, reaſon wyll tell me what is ryghte, I wyll laye to my handes, and I wyll be iuſtifyed by my dedes, drawen out and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Not ſo ye wycked perſonnes, not ſo, heare and take hede of the holy wordes of ſcripture, and the proude phariſaicall ſprete ſhall haue hys combe cut. The Iſrahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites dyd caſte in theyr myndes whan the lawe was ſette forth that they coulde do all thynges, lokynge on Moſes face whiche was couered: But it was ſayde vnto them Deuteronomi. the .v. Chapter: Who can geue them ſuch a minde to feare me, and to kepe my commaundementes? Surely iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyenge begynneth at feare and loue. But ye ſe that they haue not the feare of the Lorde, nor ſuche a mynde as can do ony good of it ſelfe. Therfore in Deutero. xxx. ſayeth Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes. The Lorde ſhal circumciſe thyne harte.
<pb facs="tcp:4840:13"/>
and Ezechiel. xi. I wyll take away the ſtony hartes. And Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .vi. Ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to me, excepte my father draw hym. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye ypocrytes learne of the lawe youre dewty, febleneſſe and paynes, and when ye fele Moſes handes heuy, flye to hym for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curre with all your harte, the which Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. viii. is deſcrybed to be the fulfiller of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe. Math. xi. Chriſt promyſed reſt of the ſoule to all them that be laden. For when we do the beſte that lyeth in vs, we beyng euell trees, brynge fyrth euell frutes, that is to ſaye we ſynne. For ſuch as euery man is, ſuche thynges dothe he thynke, ſpeake and worke. But we be fleſhe therfor we ſauour of fleſhly thynges. Why do we not graunte with ſaynt Auſtin in the boke of true inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan a man lyueth after his owne way and not after God, he is lyke the deuel: for an angel ſhulde not haue lyued after an angell, but after God, that he myght ſtonde in the trueth. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath nought of hym ſelf, but lyeng and ſynne: but yf a man haue ony trueth or ryghteouſneſſe, he hath it of the welle, which is Chriſte: And that which we haue by goddes lyberalite, hangeth of gods power, and not of oure myght. Fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider me well the wordes of the holy gooſt. Ro. ix
<pb facs="tcp:4840:14"/>
where he calleth his owne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Roma. viii. The children of God, be led with the ſprite of god. Eſaie. xxvi. Lorde thou haſt wrought all our workes in vs.</p>
                  <p>Therfore knowlege thyſelf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> handy worke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almyghty maker, ordened in Chiſte Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu to brynge forth good workes, that he hath ordeyned (marke which he hath ordeyned) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld worke in them Epheſ. ii. Therfore that thou conſenteſt to the inſpiracion of God, haſt a good wyll, and workeſt wel: the grace of god worketh all theſe thynges in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. Thou in dede co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenteſt, wylleſte, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt: but god maketh the to conſente, wyll, and worke, ſo that thys ſayng alſo may be alwayes iuſtly layd before thyne eyes: what haſt thou, that thou haſt not receaued? Yf thou haſt receaued it of other, why doeſt thou reioyce &amp; boaſte, as though thou had<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt not receaued it? i. Corinth. iiii. Not to vs Lorde, not vnto vs, but to thy name geue prayſe. Behold nowe not thy frewyll but bounde. But yf the ſonne delyuer the, then ſalte thou be truly fre. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii. For we be delyuered from ſyn by Chriſt, that we may ſerue ryghteouſneſſe. Roma. vi.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of fayth &amp; workes, the newe learnynge.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4840:14"/>
                  <p>Not onely faythe iuſtifyeth, for workes iuſtifye alſo, and fayth may ſtande and be without, good fruts &amp; grace that iuſtifieth in hym that is a breaker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god. Therfore ther are two kyndes of rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſes neceſſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is to wyte of fayth &amp; workes. The one without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other (excepte a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue no tyme or leaſur) doth not ſaue a man.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learninge.</head>
                  <p>We ſuppoſe that a man is iuſtifyed by fayth without the dedes of the lawe. Ro. iii. Here the Apoſtell doth not doute or geſſe (as ſom do vnderſtonde hym a myſſe) for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe of the greke hath we reken or gather by reaſon: For Theophilactus doth expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de thys word &amp; ſayth ſillogizometha, as though by reaſonynge he gathered thys foreſayde ſayenge. Wherfore workes do not iuſtifye, but fayth. And this is not my dreame, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt pure doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iii. &amp; .iiii. to the Roma. Where as the Apoſtell reaſonyng by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng iuſtifyed, moſt euidently proueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fayth is rekened to vs for righteouſnes. Yf Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayth he) was iuſtified by his works, he hath where vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may boaſt, but not before god
<pb facs="tcp:4840:15"/>
For what ſayeth the ſcripture? Geneſt. xv. Abraham gaue credence to God, and that was rekened vnto hym for righteouſneſſe. And in the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth <abbr>chapt</abbr> he ſayeth: That it was not wrytten for hym onely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was rekened to hym for ryghteouſneſſe, but alſo for vs, to whome it ſhal be rekened. Nother vnderſtandeth he here onely the ceremonyall workes of the lawe, but alſo of the .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandementes, the which is playne. Roma. iii. when he ſayde that no man was iuſtifyed by the workes of the lawe, ſhortly after he ſayeth: For the knowlege of ſyn is thorow the lawe. The which clauſe doth ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhewe, of what workes, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe he ſpeaketh. Yf it be ſo that oure workes alſo do iuſtifye, than Chriſt geueth but the halfe of oure ſaluacion, and then how many ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueours ſhal ther be? Ther is onely but one iuſtifyer and ſaueoure, that is Chriſte: by whome we be iuſtifyed frely, thorow hys grace. Roma. iii. Thefore workes do not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye, but fayth in Chriſte: not that fayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcoolmen cal informis (that is a dead fayth) but that true and lyuyng faythe, workynge by charite. Gala. v. chapt. lykewyſe as we be iuſtifyed before god by fayth, the which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true iuſtifycacion: ſo before men (that ſe vs
<pb facs="tcp:4840:15"/>
in the face) we be iuſtifyed by workes: that is to ſaye we be knowen to be ryghteous by the frute of good workes, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thynge the wordes of ſaynt Iames ought to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtonde: ſo he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll loke well on Paules diſputacion of fayth and workes, ſhall eaſely perceaue, why y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſaye that faythe alone iuſtifyeth. For we fayne not with this word alone, a fayth that is wthout charite, but we ſhew that workes be not the begynnyng of oure iuſtifycacion. Alſo we be not ſaued by workes. Titum. iii. but accordynge to the mercy of god, thorow the lauour of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion, and by renewynge of the holy gooſt leſt ony man ſhulde boaſte of man. Good workes are not forbydden by this doctrine, but faythe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> welle of good workes is taught and vnto grace is geuen that is hyr dewty. Parte of the prayſe is geuen vnto vs, by the newe learnyng of ſcoolmen, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thynge how blaſphemous a thyng it is, the faythful Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men can tell. And ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old learnyng taketh not away workes, but ſetteth them in theyr place, that they maye be witneſſes of our fayth, ſubdue the fleſhe, &amp; ſerue our neyghbour, but not that they ſhuld iuſtifye: ſeynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> onely fayth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mere mercy of god thorow his worde doth iuſtifye a man. The
<pb facs="tcp:4840:16"/>
perſon that is iuſtified, worketh iuſtly, yet for al that, it doth not boaſte of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of workes as neceſſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſte when it ſeketh his owne righteouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, it leſe the ryghteouſneſſe of God, that is faythe. Roma. x. And it graunteth the very truth with Eſay .lxiiii. That the ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of his workes, is lyke a fylthy clothe, defyled with the flours of a woman. And he an vnprofitable ſeruaunt. The which is onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way to come to true ryghteouſneſſe of oure workes. That is when thou wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng beſely, yet in al thy workes knowlegeſt thy ſelf a ſynner: &amp; flye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge onely to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the mediatour, ſetteſt muche by the pryce of oure redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n For yf the ryghteouſneſſe of our workes, be of ony value, the death of Chriſte hath not wholy and fully wrought oure ſaluacion, the whiche is blaſphemous. The ſhort argument of Paule ſtondeth and is ſure and vnmoueable: Yf the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe come of the lawe, then is Chriſte dead in vayne: But Chriſt dyed not in vayne, therfore ye boaſte in vayne of the ryghteouſneſſe of workes and of the lawe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of meryte or deſeruynge, the newe learnynge</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4840:16"/>
                  <p>Whan we do that lyeth in vs i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drawynge out of a good mocion towarde god by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll, we deſerue the fyrſte grace of congruite &amp; ſemlyneſſe, although not of worthynes. Alſo the ſoule endued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grace by an acte drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frewyll &amp; of grace deſerueth worthely euerlaſtynge lyfe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde chriſten reader, whan as carnall wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall heare that ſhe hath ſuch power, and can drawe forth by naturall power a good mocion towarde God, &amp; may deſerue therby, wyll ſhe not fall to the phariſaycall pryde? and wyll ſhe not attribute to her ſelfe it that pertayneth to god? The whiche is nothynge elles, but to treade vnder fete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of god, and to reken the bloud of the teſtamente but as an vnholy and a ꝓphane thynge, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we be fanctifyed. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer oure nature which leaneth and ſetteth to muche by her ſelfe, ſwellynge wyth thys learnynge, is brought into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. For nature hearyng that we partly can deſerue euerlaſtynge lyfe with oure dedes: wyll enforce herſelfe to heape together me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes: the whiche beyng many and plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſhe wyl truſte and haue a good hope in them: and when they fayle an decay, ſhe wyll fall in to deſpayre: by the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4840:17"/>
errour the worthyneſſe and deſeruyng of Chryſtes death is defaced and hyd wyth darcknes, and mans conſcience is buylded vpon the ſonde of workes, and ſurely at euery tempeſte of tribulacion it wyll fall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>In the ſeconde Epiſtle vnto Timothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> i. Chapter. God ſaued vs not accordyng to oure workes, but accordyng to his purpoſe and grace, which was geuen vnto vs before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſtyng tymes. Such lyke is ther alſo Tit. iii. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ephe. ii. Ye be ſaued by grace thorow fayth, and not of youre ſelues: it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyft of God, &amp; not of workes, leſte ony man ſhulde boaſte. The ſcripture here taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the cauſe of deſeruynge or merite fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure workes, and geueth to grace that we be ſaued. For that he ſayth: not accordyng to our workes, and alſo: not of yow, ſuerly he doth not admitte or receaue that acte or dede that is drawen out of wyll, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayſe of ſaluacion or merite. Chriſte deſerued all thinges vnto vs with his bloud. And we are iuſtifyed frely Roma. iii. The heretage was not gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by oure laboure, but by Chriſtes. The fayth in Chriſte maketh vs ſonnes, therefor heyres: ergo, workes do it not. Ro.
<pb facs="tcp:4840:17"/>
iiii. To hym that worketh is the rewarde not rekened of fauoure, but of deutye. To hym that worketh not, but beleueth in hym that iuſtifyeth the vngodly, is fayth cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for ryghteouſneſſe. Ro. viii. For I ſuppoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the affliccyons of this lyfe, are not worthy the glory which ſhalbe ſhewed vpon vs. Lu. vii. Whan ye haue done all thynges that be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded you, yet ſaye that ye be vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyble ſeruauntes. Eſay. lxiiii. All our ryghte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſneſſes are as a defyled cloth. &amp;c. i. Corin. iiii. What haſte thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt not recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Rom. xi. Who hath geuen hym oughte afore hande, that he myght be recompenced agayn? Philip. ii. It is God which worketh in you, both the wyll &amp; alſo the dede, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good wyll. Yf ſo be that God worketh in vs goodneſſe, what ſhal we arrogau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly clayme and aſcrybe there vpon to oure power and ſtrength? And yf we deſerue the blyſſe, why doth ſcripture cal it grace? Therfore be not we ſaued by oures, but onely by the workes &amp; merytes of Chriſt. But where as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſomtyme maketh mencyon of rewarde ther can no man there vpon take iuſte oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſyon to ſwell and be proude: for fayth wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge by charite is the gyfte of God, good workes are the gyfte of God, ſo that, yf
<pb facs="tcp:4840:18"/>
God do rewarde vs, we muſte vnderſtande that he doth not rewarde oure workes, but his owne workes in vs. But thou yf thou clayme ony thynge there vpon to thy ſelfe, then ſhalte thou receaue no reward of glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye wyth the wycked pharyſes, but thou ſhalte fele the punyſhment of the fyre of hell. And ſeynge that it is ſo, it maye be eaſely iudged, who teacheth more truely. I wyth the Apoſtle do alwayes exorte me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the true good workes, whiche be done in fayth, alwayes takynge hede that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by reaſon of them, truſt not in hymſelfe, and be reproued with the pharyſe. They do ſo pricke and moue vnto good workes, that they reſte and put in them the hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon, and the cauſe of merites: wherby at chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth that euery where men do them wyth this falſe opinion, to be iuſtifyed and ſaued by them. We not deſpyſynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God, do teach, both y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be ſaued only by the grace of God, and we buylde mens conſcyences not vpon workes, but vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone that is Chriſt, agaynſt the whiche the gates of hell can not preuayle, and do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beate in this mooſt confortable goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, or glad tydynges. That heretage is ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen by fayth, that the promyſes may be ſure
<pb facs="tcp:4840:18"/>
after grace. As ſayeth Paul Ro. iiii. and .v. We iuſtifyed by fayth, haue peace wyth God thorowe Chriſte.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of ſynne. The new learnynge.</head>
                  <p>The luſt or concupiſcence that remay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth in a man after baptyme, the lawe of the membres, infirmitie, or ſyckneſſe, is no ſynne nother veniall nor mortall, and after baptyme it is not original, but is the payne of ſynne. Neuertheleſſe it bryngeth forth ſynne. This opinion maketh a man that is baptyſed ſlowe and dull to fyght agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe, for he beleueth that he is all whole &amp; in ſauegarde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Concupiſcence which ſheweth her ſelfe by hir euell frutes, euen in a man that is baptyſed, is ſynne of her ſelfe. Ro. vii. Here the Apoſtle ſayeth: Now I myne owne ſelfe do not this, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynne which dwelleth &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayneth in me. The Apoſtel doth not here ſpeake i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon of wycked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for wycked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, they ſerue &amp; obey not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr mynde. S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme of this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the apoſtle had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe wordes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon of euel men, but i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his retractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; againſt Iulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth reuoke this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and he ſayd that at that
<pb facs="tcp:4840:19"/>
tyme he vnderſtode not Apoſtell aryght. Now he that ſpeaketh ſo, and was baptyſed, and was the electe inſtrument of God, and yet complayneth of concupiſcence and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it ſynne, then let the ſcooleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tell, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the Apoſtell doth well call that concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, which bryngeth forth euell frutes (excepte it be ſtopped) ſynne or no? Yee let them tell whether the holy gooſt dyd erre in that worde. Verely .i. Corin. xiiii. the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell thanketh God that he ſpake more wyth tunges, then all the Corinthians dyd. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſo great an Apoſtell knewe with what wordes he ſhuld name concupiſcence. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we folowe that maner of ſpeakyng, we are chaced out, mocked, and caſt out as herety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of them that are lytell moued, with the cauſe of ſo great matters, ſo that they may triumphe in the worlde and lyue in peace. Then the trueth is, that concupiſcence (the which bryngeth forth the ſame frutes after baptyme that it dyd before) is called ſynne: as the Apoſtel doth exhorte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſed, Ro. vi. Let not ſynne reygne in your mortall bodyes. He doth not ſaye concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, but ſynne, for ſo the trueth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greke hath. Moreouer ther is no man but he kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth that ſynne is knowen by the lawe, but
<pb facs="tcp:4840:19"/>
this concupiſcence is forboden of the lawe, for it is ſynne. Infirmityes ſurely &amp; alſo pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes do not fall vnder the precepte. And it is knowen that the Apoſtell ſayeth Ro. vii. I dyd not knowe ſynne, but by the lawe, for I had not knowen that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence had ben a ſynne, yf the lawe had not ſayd thou ſhalt not luſt, and by and by he calleth it ſynne. But this is the difference, namely before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptyme of the ſprete and water, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence or luſt was a ſynne raygnynge, but after the waſſhynge of regeneration, it is ſynne ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me and ſubdued: of his own nature in dede it is euell, but a man truely regenerate, and not walkynge after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, doth repreſſe and holde downe ſynne with the ſpret of grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it raygne not, nor haue the ouerhande, that ther be no damnacyon vnto them that be grafted in Chriſt. Roma. viii. For it is not rekened hym to damnaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the ſprete that reſyſteth the fleſhe. The whiche thynge ſaynt Auſten in theſe wordes doth conclude: All ſynne is forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in baptyme, not that it ſhulde not be at all, but that it ſhulde not be rekened for ſynne. Now iudge good reader, which of vs ſpeake more truly: they that make ſo lyght a thyng of this olde leuen of malyce, callynge it a
<pb facs="tcp:4840:20"/>
lytel infirmite onely, whiche neuertheleſſe is no veniall ſynne, do not know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god, &amp; do blaſpheme vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> make a great thing of it: as it is a great thynge in very dede, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde haue nede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great grace of God. We do exalte &amp; magnifye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kynde de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocion &amp; godlynes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of Chriſt: where w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al ſynne is pourged &amp; redemed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſours &amp; grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters of our ſynnes, may fynde grace in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes of god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſte iudge.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of worſhippynge of ſayntes. The new</head>
                  <p>Not only Chriſt is our mediatour, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſayntes which raygne in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſt: wherfor they ought to be called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as mediatours of interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe vnto vs many good thinges. Our Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de diuidyng his kyngdom hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the one halfe of his kyngdom, (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is mercy) to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes, to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and diſtributed vnto the worlde: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other part (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is iudgement) he ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth behynde for himſelfe. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ony thynge of a prynce he ſeketh out ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of authorite, at whoſe requeſt he may obtayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl haue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ſhulde not ſpede yf he came to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince alone. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother of God yf ſhe brake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heade of the old ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, why ſhuld ſhe not be a meane for mankinde? Therfore our lady &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes do worke partly our ſaluation. The bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:4840:20"/>
virgin is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neck, Chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head, &amp; we be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres: no good gyftes come downe into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres, but thorow Mary as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> necke. Alſo the ſaintes worke miracles. For how many beyng ſyck w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuerſe ſickneſſes, haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes of the ſaintes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>A ſynner alone maye not appeare in the ſyght of God, (for our god is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumynge fyre. Heb. xiii.) except he be brought to hym by a mediatour, for whoſe merites ſake he doth forgeue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynners treſpaſſes. Chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mediatour .i. Timo. ii. Heb. ix. Ro. viii. our ſatiſfaccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .i. Io. ii. our ryghteouſneſſe .i. Cor i. our preſt for euer, Pſal. cix. Heb. iiii.v.vii.viii.ix.x. Chriſt is not a fearfull iudge to faythful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but an aduocate, callyng vnto him thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Mat. xi. He is of ſo great mercy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he gaue his lyfe for his ſhepe. Io. x. Mat. xx. Then we ought not to be afrayed of Chriſte, as yf he were a iudge, but we ought to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trone of grace, becauſe we be ſynners, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo we myght be delyuered of ſynne: for he is the lambe. &amp;c. Mat. ix. Lu. v. He came not in to this world to cal rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men. &amp;c. A ſyck man feareth not a phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſicyan, but the ſycker that he is the more deſyrous he is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phiſicyan. Shall that phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſicyan
<pb facs="tcp:4840:21"/>
which dyed for vs, when we were yet ſynners. Ro. v. be now vnconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and do no thinge but threaten &amp; kyl, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue nede of ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to playe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mediatour &amp; meane betwene hym &amp; vs, to ſwage his wrath? O vnſemynge thought of a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What a carnall and a fleſhly dreame is this? How fonde a kinde of fellowes are theſe? how vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>learned in the ſcripture? Who dyed for vs? dyd Steuen or Peter? Dyd not Chriſt dye for vs? &amp; that of ſuche a charite, as is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be expreſſed. Io. xv. Greater loue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this can no man haue, euen that a man be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtowe his lyfe for his frendes. And yet for al that great charite we dreame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt is a fearfull tyraunt &amp; that he wyll put awaye a wretched ſynner nedynge a phiſicyan, with a cruel cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte hym to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentours, excepte he brynge ſome ſaynt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym. So worſhip we now the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God which humbled hymſelfe to the death of the croſſe, that we not beleuynge his wordes, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayeth: Come to me &amp; I ſhall refreſh you, I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye, I beſtowe my lyfe for my ſhepe, but dare be ſo bolde as to accuſe hym of lyeng, &amp; ſay theſe be voyde wordes which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt ſay. Thou haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted mercy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaintes, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt do nothing els but threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4840:21"/>
vndo ſynners. I wyll turne me to ſome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes which ſhalbe me patrone and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate by the. Are not theſe ſaynges wicked &amp; vngodly? yet they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wolde be rekened mooſt holy of all, be of thys mynde and opinion, &amp; they condemne vs of hereſye before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be knowen. The ſcripture byddeth vs axe in the name of Chriſte, ſuch thynge as we haue nede of, Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xvi. and not in the name of ſayntes. Reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliacion &amp; ſaluation is in none other name. Actu. iiii. The preſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode of Chriſte is for euermore. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtell ſayeth. Ro. viii. that Chriſt remayneth &amp; abydeth at the ryght hande of the father &amp; maketh interceſſion for vs. He is onely the way to the father. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xiiii. By hym we haue an entrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father Ephe ii. By hym we haue boldneſſe and intrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to god in all confidence thorow the fayth in hym. Ephe. iii. He is oure hope .i. Timoth. i. He came that he myght ſaue ſynners. i. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth. i. He gaue hym ſelf an oblacion to god for vs Epheſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. v. And we amonge ſo many prayſes of burnyng charite &amp; fre mercy haue not learned yet to truſte in hym, whiche is our reconcyler, and brynger in fauour ſo ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell and lyberall, that he dyd not dyſdayne to be an oblacion for ſyn for vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we myght
<pb facs="tcp:4840:22"/>
be made the ryghteouſneſſe of god thorow hym: ſo myghty, that they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleue in hym, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be aſhamed. Roma. ix. Farther more the mother that is a virgyne vſurpeth or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto her none of thoſe thynges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſynge to hyr prayſe. I pray yow for ſhame darre the corrupters of ſcripture geue that vnto the mother, which the holy gooſt dyd prophecy of the ſonne of God. Geneſis iii? For he and not ſhe dyd breake the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes head. In ſomuch that I can not tel whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhuld maruayl more vpon the groſſe &amp; ruſtical ignoraunce of theſe greate maſters or that I ſhulde crye out vpon the wycked &amp; vngodly opinion that they haue of Chryſte. They haue ſo lytell regarde what they ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al the thought that they take is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alwayes they ſhulde be ſayenge ſomthynge. And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as in tymes paſte the philoſophers of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures ſecte and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Stoykes affyrmed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God dyd none other wayes, and had no other ſubſiſtence, then they thought he had: and ſubſcrybed the nature of God with vayne dreames &amp; deuyces of theyr opinions, lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe oure falſe diuynes do ymagen Chriſte to geue from hym his mercy to ſayntes, and to be a fearfull iudge, and that he dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all ſynners, excepte that he be pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:4840:22"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> ſwaged by the interceſſion of ſome ſaynte. And this ymaginacion pleaſeth them well, and they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the church ſo to beleue. Alſo theſe fellowes make Mary the necke of the myſticall body. Who can abſtayne from laughyng (yee rather wepynge.) They make artycles of the fayth beſyde the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of theyr owne brayne, and where they ſhuld onely ſtycke to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, they bryng forth old wyues fables for ſounde and true thynges, meſurynge al godly thynges wyth the plummet or lyne of our reaſon, and by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimilytudes of thys world. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they tryfle bothe vnlearnedly and vngodly, yet they be not afrayed to dryue to the fyre as many as wyll not play the fooles with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And that in all poyntes they may play the falſe doctors they wrafte the ſcriptures to confirme theyr errours, of the which thyng I haue ſpoken very largely in oure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne places. But left ony man ſhuld thynke that I ſaye thys in the reproche of ſayntes, ſo I thynke: that ſayntes ſhuld be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, but after the rule of ſcripture. Seynge that they be the glorious membres of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticall body, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſhold meny of God, and ioyned vnto vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mooſt ſureſt bonde of charite. For charite peryſheth not, but is
<pb facs="tcp:4840:23"/>
made perfect in heauen: wherfore they loue vs, and couet with a brotherly loue oure amendment. Therfore let vs reuerently &amp; holyly kepe the memory and remembraunce of them, in the which we may ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſdom of God, his goodneſſe, power and the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpeakeable ryches of mercy, to the exercyſe of our fayth hope and charyte. For as ofte as we remembre theyr manly fyghtyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the gates of hell, and the manyfold grace of god, the which the father of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort poured forth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe veſſels of mercy we are lyfted vp in hope and truſte of ſo great goodneſſe. And we be prouoked to the folowynge of ſo greate perſeueraunce by theyr vertues, ſet out as whement intyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. What good and deuout ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ther but he wyll deſyre with all his hart, that he myght ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemye of owre ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with ſuche ſtrength of fayth as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes were endued and harneſſed with all, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at the laſte hys enemyes ouercome, he myght be aſſociate and acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panyed for euer more, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> electe and choſen of god? And whan he doth ſe ſo excellent veſſels of glory made of the chyldren of wrathe, and of the lompe of perdicion, not by mans merites, but by the power of the grace of god: that
<pb facs="tcp:4840:23"/>
he wyll conceaue a truſty hope of ſo mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a father, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which made vs worthy when he founde vs vnworthy. Then yf we pray to God for fayth, hope, and charite. And ſeke the kyngdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before al other thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, we maye folow the footeſteppes of the ryght ſayntes, then haue we worſhipped the ſayntes very well, and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as we ſhulde do. For the wyl of God and the ſayntes is one, wherfore what other thynge wyll they axe, then the amendement of a ſynner, and the contynuall recordyng and remembraunce of the lawes of God. But that we ſhulde flye for ſuccurre to them, in oure aduerſite &amp; nede, that they may be meanes betwene vs and God, they nother do require it: for they ſeke nothynge but the glory of God, nother can we deſyre them to be mediatours for vs excepte we do iniury to the mooſt perfyte &amp; mooſt ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mediatour of all. Now ſeyng that the ſcripture is our candell, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt darke nyght of thys world, we be more ſure that call vpon God by Chriſte (the whiche thynge the ſcripture doth commaunde) then they which imagen new kyndes of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng and inuocacions, of the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture maketh no mencion at all. Call vpon me (ſayeth the Lord) in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4840:24"/>
&amp; I ſhall delyuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> and thou ſhalt honor me. Pſalmo. xlvi. And Ioel. ii. Whoſoeuer wyll call on the name of God for helpe ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And in thys matter we force not vpon long tyme or longe coſtume: for chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or a chriſten mans lyuyng, ſtandeth, not in the paſſyng ouer of longe tyme, or in the oldneſſe or antiquite of coſtume, but in the ſcriptures of euerlaſtyng truth.</p>
                  <p>Now good reader iudge what kynne of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men they be, that faſten theyr hope not in Chriſte, but in creatures, knowyng no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge at all how muche helpe we haue in Chriſte. They differ very lyttell from ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrers, &amp; whyle they go aboute mooſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to honoure ſayntes, they dyſhonour them farre out of rule and faſhion that can be: euen when they geue away from god to the creature hope and confidence, the which is dew onely to god. As touchyng the myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles reade the .xxiiii. chapter of Math. and the ſeconde of the .ii. Epiſtell to the Teſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonyans, &amp; youre mynde ſhalbe at reſte and certifyed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſupper of the Lorde, The newe learnynge.</head>
                  <p>The ſacrament of the aultare muſte be
<pb facs="tcp:4840:24"/>
geuen onely vnto preſtes vnder both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and to lay men onely vnder the kynde of bread, becauſe that Chriſte by a naturall accompaninge or folowyng is whole vnder bothe the kyndes, accordyng vnto that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge of the ſequence: The fleſh is meate, &amp; bloud is dryncke, Chriſte abydeth for al that whole vnder both the kyndes. A lay man muſt take his ryghtes euery yeare once at the leaſte accordyng to the chapter Omnis vtriuſque. &amp;c. The maſſe of a preſt is a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce both for quyck and dead, and the ſyn &amp; the vncleneſſe of the perſon of the miniſter ſtoppeth not the frute, ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wrought worke of the maſſe hath ſtrength, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blacion is made in the perſon of the whole church: wherefore it is a great merite, for by it we deſerue muche to oure ſelues, and alſo to other. Wherfore the ordinaunces of maſſes be good, and yearly obytes be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable. For in other good workes the wyckedneſſe of the perſon of the miniſter taketh awaye the cauſe of the merite: here it letteth nothynge, where as the faythe of the churche is conſydered, and not the worthyneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon. Thys is the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me: A wycked man and an vngodly, hauyng on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a dewe intent, although he be an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynable
<pb facs="tcp:4840:25"/>
in the ſyght of God, yet for al that in thys cauſe, becauſe he beareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne or is in the rowme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, he abydyng a ſynner and a da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable perſon, he purchaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and deſerueth vnto other men, remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of ſyn and euerlaſtyng lyfe. This they ſaye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>The Apoſtell in the fyrſt epiſtell to the Corinthians the .xi. chapter, preparyng the ſupper of the Lorde, dyd wryte that he toke of the Lorde that he taught and gaue to the Corinthians. And whan he expounded the buſyneſſe and matter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the ſupper he geueth both the kyndes indifferently to all the bretheren, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Chriſt dyd ordeyne. Mathe. xxvi. Marke. xiiii. Luke. xxii. Here we haue the worde and the facte of the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and of hys miniſter Paule and alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primitiue church, in the which as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth was more lyuely, charite was more feruent hope was more ſure, and holy chriſtendom was more purer, for it was nearer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quycke ſprynge. Yf it be ſo that it is not leful for vs to kepe the worde and the dede of Chriſt, &amp; ſpecially in a great mater, as is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for what intent ſhall the churche of God
<pb facs="tcp:4840:25"/>
haue the ſcripture expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and declared? Dyd not euen the new wryters (as Gerſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ſaye: That nother the byſhop of Rome nor generall councell, nor yet the church oughte to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the learnynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was geuen vs by the euangeliſtes, &amp; by Paul? Yf it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to euery man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyſt, to chaunge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, thoſe thynges which Chriſt taught to be kept, &amp; the apoſtles both taught and kept: I pray you what caſe ſhall the church be in then, which ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſedome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, &amp; the Apoſtels dyd teach chriſtendom ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perfecte geare &amp; ſo negligently y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours had nede to ſupplye, ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; make perfecte thoſe thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt &amp; his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels lefte behynde them raw &amp; vnperfect? Wyll the Saracens, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arabia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; the Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens (whome we call Turkes) ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at his pleaſure after this faſhion ſhulde chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge theyr Alcoram, &amp; wolde ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme take ſomthyng away, ſomtyme vtterly abrogate &amp; diſanul it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr lawmaker had wrytten, ſomthynge vnwarely, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out diligent hede &amp; delyberacyon? And we chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> except we ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church to be turned out of fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; peruerted, to be darkened &amp; to be pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ſunder &amp; miniſhed, Yee to be vtterly
<pb facs="tcp:4840:26"/>
caſt awaye, we be banyſhed &amp; deſtroyed as the enemyes of the church. Put the caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe be tollerable: who can abyde that ydel felowes ſhall make marchaundyſe of it that was lefte to be the memoriall and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the death whiche brought lyfe, wherby they make a ſacrifyce of the maſſe, &amp; crucifye Chriſt agayne, as much as lyeth in them? For yf it be ſo that they worke with theyr dayly ſacrifyce (as they call it) remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of ſynne, I praye you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ſynnes dyd the bloude of the new &amp; euerlaſtyng te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtament take awaye? This is therfore our catholyke belefe of the ſupper of the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>Fyrſt: The ſupper of the Lord ought for to be done after the ordinaunce of Chriſte i. Cor. xi. that our fayth maye be increaced, our charite may be kyndled, our hope maye be made ſure, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of the death of the Lorde: &amp; that we knowyng the cauſe of the mooſt precyous death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, maye be dayly more and more ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp, to geue thankes for the vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue, to deſtroye the body of ſynne and to walke in newneſſe of lyfe.</p>
                  <p>Secondarly, Therfore the ſupper of the Lorde is a memoriall of the death of Chriſte, whiche brought ſaluacyon and not
<pb facs="tcp:4840:26"/>
a ſacrifyce, but a remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was once offred vp vpon the croſſe.</p>
                  <p>Thyrdly, Ther is a promes. Pſal. c.ix. that Chriſt ſhalbe our byſhop for euermore ordened of the father: and this promes is perfourmed, for Chriſt hath entred once in to the holy place, by an oblacyon makynge perfect for euermore. Hebr. ix. and .x. ſo that we nede not to haue hym offred vp for vs agayne, the which dyeth nomore.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, We knowe of the boke Leui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticus, that the oblacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Moſes was made for ſynnes, whan the oblacyon dyd ſatiſfye and the bloude dyd waſhe. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf this one ſacrifyce, (in the which Chriſt dyd offer vp hymſelfe) dyd ſatiſfye for the ſynnes of the whole worlde, accordynge to the prophecye of Eſay. the .liii. Chapter. He dyd beare our ſynnes, and he was torne for oure wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and .i. Ioh. the .ii. Chapter. He is oure ſatiſfaccyon and ſo forth: it foloweth and is a good argument, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the oblacyons which are beſyde this, be vayne and voyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they pretende?</p>
                  <p>Fyftly, To rayſe vp a new oblacyon is to ſet lytel by the fyrſt, to proue God a lyar and to deny Chriſte whiche bought vs, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the wordes of ſaynt Peter .ii. Pet. ii.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4840:27"/>
                  <p>For whan they ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſynnes be releaſſed &amp; forgeuen in the ſacrifice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God is offered vp both for quycke &amp; dead, it foloweth after theyr opinion, that that onely ſacrifice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe dyd not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye for all ſynnes. And I praye you is not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euen to forſweare &amp; denye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde which dyd redeme vs, not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> corruptible thynges, as with golde &amp; ſyluer but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his owne preci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous bloud, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is done by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which al ſcripture doth ſay co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to vs by the death of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>Syxtly. Yet for al that we do not affirme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynnes be remytted only by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partakynge of the ſupper of the Lorde, but whan we do reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a true &amp; a kynde fayth the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte of our redemption, in the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of god dyd geue his body a ſacrifyce for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, &amp; ſhed his bloud to waſhe away ſynne: by this fayth we be iuſtifyed &amp; made rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, &amp; we obtayne remiſſyon of our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, gotten by the death of Chriſt. And this is a dilicyous feaſt of ſoules, of the whiche they that are not partakers ſhall peryſhe.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt in the .vi. Chap. of Ihon ſayeth. My fleſhe is meate in dede, and my bloude is drynke in dede. The bread that I ſhal geue,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:27"/>
is my fleſh the which I wyll geue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of the worlde. Excepte we eate this fleſhe of the ſonne of man and drynke his bloud, we ſhall not haue lyfe in vs, but we ſhal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe. For it is the breade of lyfe, geuynge lyfe to the worlde. The whiche breade to eate, is to beleue in Chriſt as he ſayeth: I am the bread of lyfe, he that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to me ſhall not be an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gred, and he that beleueth in me ſhall neuer be thyrſty. Verely verely I ſaye vnto you, he that truſteth in me hath euerlaſtynge lyfe. For as the body is fed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> naturall bread, ſo the ſoule is refreſhed &amp; ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth with this heauenly bread. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule beleueth that Chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryce of oure redemption, our ſatiſfaccyon, and our rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, with this fayth it eateth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, and drynketh the bloude, and accordynge to the wordes of Chriſt Ioh. vi. by ſo wholſome an eatyng ſhal we lyue for euer. Theſe be ſo great thynges which be rehearſed aboute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table of the Lorde. God graunt that this ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remony of Chriſte, maye be reſtored to hys olde ſtrength and integrite agayne, that we which be the body of Chriſt oure heade, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed of the loue of God in the ſupper towarde vs, maye growe together with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſable glew of loue, as it becommeth
<pb facs="tcp:4840:28"/>
membres, purgynge the flocke with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boult of excommunicacyon, and eatynge truely the fleſhe of the Lorde, that is to beleue in Chriſte crucifyed, and that we may be graf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in hym by the lykeneſſe of his death, and that we maye be partakers wyth hym, of the mooſt gloryous reſurreccyon.</p>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of the choyſe of meates. The new learnynge.</head>
                  <p>It is not lawfull to eate euery daye all ſortes of meate, for it is neceſſary that we abſtayne from fleſhe euery frydaye and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdaye, and on the embrynge dayes and in lent: for he that doth otherwyſe without the Biſſhop of Romes bulles or the pardons of the legates of the ſye of Rome, doth ſyn, and ſhalbe rekened an euell chriſten man, yee a wycked and an vngodly heretyke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>In the .xi. Chapter of Leuiticus, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xiiii. of Deuteronomion, the choyſe of mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes is preſcribed vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, which were vnder Moſes, ſo that it was not lawfull to eate what ſo euer meate they lyſte. But let vs which are commaunded of Paul to the
<pb facs="tcp:4840:28"/>
Gal. the .v. Chapter. to ſtande faſt in the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte, in to the which Chriſte hath brought vs, and that we ſhulde not put our neckes vnder the yocke of bondage agayne, geue hede and attendaunce what oure mayſter Chriſt and Lorde doth ſaye: Math. xv. Hear and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: It that goeth in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth defyleth not the man, but it that goeth out of the mouth that defyleth a man. Theſe wordes of Chriſt take awaye the choyſe of meates ſo that it is lawful in the tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to eate fleſh or fyſhe whether ye wyll without ony ſynne. In the fyrſte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtel to Timo. the .iiii. Chap, the holy gooſt doth call the forbyddynge of meate &amp; of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riage, the doctrine of the deuell: For God hath created meate to be receaued with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of thankes of them which beleue, &amp; haue knowen the trueth: for the creatures of God are good, and nothynge to be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yf it be receaued with thankes geuyng: for it is ſanctifyed by the worde of God &amp; prayer. By this one texte of the Apoſtle is plucked vp by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rootes, what ſo euer hether to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue taught or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choyſe of meates. For the holy gooſt calleth it dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelyſh doctrine the whiche no man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kepe &amp; obey w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the loſſe of his ſaluacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let it
<pb facs="tcp:4840:29"/>
moue no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſaynt Ierome doth wraſt theſe ſayenges agaynſte the Tacyans and the Marcionites, doutleſſe our conſciences be delyuered from the choyſe of meates by theſe wordes of the holy gooſt. Therfore who ſo euer he be, Marcyon or ony of this tyme that byndeth wyth a commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that thynge which Chriſt wolde haue to be fre, he is reproued wyth this texte as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde to God, and a deſpyſer of a good cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ature. Colloſſenſes the .ii. Chapter ſayeth Paule: Let no man iudge you in meat and drynke. Yf you be dead wyth Chriſte from the elementes of the worlde, why be you holden wyth decrees, as yf ye were lyuyng in the worlde? This texte alſo is playne agaynſte all the prayſers and preachers of mans tradicyons, the whiche do trouble mens conſcyences wyth mans preceptes, of the choyſe of meates. Although thys maketh agaynſte the obſeruacyons of the Iewes, yet it plucketh vp by the rootes all the tradicyons of men in thys matter.</p>
                  <p>For yf Moſes lawe in that poynt be abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate and put downe, the which was once or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dened of God: how muche more iuſtly the conſtitucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to be diſanulled &amp; put awaye? by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which theſe cruel tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:4840:29"/>
coueth a kyngdome in mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. Gala. i. Yf ony man preach ony other goſpell or glad tydynges vnto you, than ye haue receaued, holde hym acurſed. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore what ſoeuer other thynge is thruſt into oure handes agaynſt and beſyde the worde of God, to bynde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, by the ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence of the holy gooſt it is acurſed, wherfor we muſt refuſe it both with hand and foote. Titum. i. Rebuke them ſharply that they may be ſound in the fayth, and not takynge hyde to Iewes fables and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of men, the which turne from the trueth.</p>
                  <p>Vnto the cleane are all thynges cleane, but to them that are defyled and vnbeleuyng is nothyng cleane, but euen the very myndes and conſciences of them are defyled. Who wolde not abhorre thoſe preceptes whyche turne from the trueth? Euen ſo the holy gooſte decketh mans tradicions w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys tytle with the which tradicion the deceauers of mens myndes go aboute to bynde mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences, where as God byddeth not. Here I do not regarde thoſhe great prayſers of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, the which wyll name me the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men as ſaynt Ierome called Iouiniane, as though I we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te about to louſe the brydell of gluttony. Teſe felowes wyll
<pb facs="tcp:4840:30"/>
diſpute with a full belly of faſtyng, and yet they eate feſans, partriches, and al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pycked dayntyes that can be found in a contry.</p>
                  <p>Now tel me I pray yow what haue I ſayde beſyde the ſentences of the holy gooſt? I do not teache the abuſe, but the ryghte vſe of the creatures of God, with geuynge than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. I take not thought onely for the belly. but alſo for the conſcience. Fo with theſe mans tradycions, mens conſciences be marked with an whote yron, and God is worſhypped wyth commaundementes of men: the whych thynge in the .xxix. of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaye, he hateth and abhorreth. It is a very ieoperdous matter to laye ſnares for mens conſciences and to offende agaynſt the chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten lyberte which coſt ſo much. Yf ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laye agaynſte vs ſaynt Ierome, or ony o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the fathers: I anſwere that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were neuer in that blyndneſſe, that they wolde be beleued more then the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He deſpiſeth not the fathers whiche enforceth hym ſelfe and laboureth to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify the father of all which is in heauen.</p>
                  <p>He that in the matter of conſcience doth thynke, that God ſhulde rather be obeyed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, doth not contemne men, but mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifyeth
<pb facs="tcp:4840:30"/>
God, the Lorde of men and angels. And the condicion and ſtate of chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not ſo, that they ought to take example or rule of lyuynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes of Iupiter, that abſteyne from fleſhe and ſoden meate, or of the temple of Eleuſis or Ceres or of Orpheus, yet that holy man is not aſhamed of hys monkery of ſo voyde wordes in the ſeconde boke agaynſte Iouinian. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge offendynge, I haue taught always accordynge to the Apoſtles doctrine Roma xiiii. that we ſhulde haue a reſpecte and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of weake perſonnes, that he that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, deſpiſe not hym that eateth not: He that eateth not, let hym not iudge hym that eateth. And albeit he ſayeth ther is nothyng vncleane of it ſelf, but vnto hym which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth that it is vncleane: yet for all that he wyll not that oure brother ſhulde be gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the abuſe of oure lyberte, and to be loſt with meate, for whom Chriſte ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered death. Ther be other farre greater thynges than meate and drynke that a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man ſhulde regarde, namely, peace and edifyenge. For the kyngdome of God is not meate and drynke, but ryghteouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and peace and ioye in the holy gooſt.</p>
                  <p>Therfore let vs folow thoſe thynges that
<pb facs="tcp:4840:31"/>
longe vnto peace and to the edifyeng of our brother one towarde another. Haſt thou fayth? kepe it to they ſelfe before God. And i. Corint. viii. Knowlege maketh ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſwel charyte edyfieth, take hede leſte youre lyber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te offend thoſe that be weake. All theſe be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholſome doctrines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt, &amp; geue none occaſion of gluttony, as the defenders of tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do dreame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of faſtynge, The newe learnynge.</head>
                  <p>We muſt faſt certayne dayes vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement, as the Apoſtels euen the .iiii. ymbrynge dayes, and the lent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Our lyfe is a warfare or ſouldyers lyfe Ioh. vii. We muſt fyght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually with an enemye that we haue at home with in vs, namely the fleſh: leſt he beynge made to fat &amp; wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with exceſſe of meate and drynke, preuayle agaynſt the ſprite. Take hede to youreſelfs (ſayth Chriſt Luc. xxi.) leſt youre hartes be ouercomme with ſurfettynge and dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe, that the daye of the Lord come not vnto you as a ſnare. Rom. xiii. doth the holy go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to caſt awaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes
<pb facs="tcp:4840:31"/>
of darkneſſe, &amp; to put on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armour of lyght, &amp; he reherſeth vnreaſonable eatynge, &amp; ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettynge &amp; dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kneſſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynte no certayne day, but onely he ſayeth make not prouyſion for the fleſh to fulfyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> luſtes of it: wyllyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld abſtayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnreaſonable eatyng and dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe, to put awaye the workes of darkneſſe: not for one or two dayes, but at all tymes: Let no man thynke that thys faſt is a chriſten mans faſt which now raygneth, is commaunded, and hygly prayſed, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we faſt certaine houres, and other dayes make luſty chere, worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng our belly for our God. In the which thynge we be worſe then the heythen men, which dyd order theyr lyuelode not to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur, but to the health and ſtrength of theyr bodyes. For they conſyderynge what excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and worthyneſſe ther is in the nature of man, dyd perceaue how fowle a thyng it were to flow in exceſſe, to lyue deliciouſly &amp; pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, and how honeſt it were to lyue ſkarſly, meſurably, ſadly and ſoberly The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle monyſſheth vs .i. Teſſalo. v. of oure ſtate and condition. We (ſayeth he) are the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lyghte and the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the daye, let vs be ſober: he byddeth vs not do ſo for .ii or .iii. dayes, but all the tyme that we beare
<pb facs="tcp:4840:32"/>
about thys body of ſynne. Who can here in ſo grat diuerſityes of complexiones preſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be meaſures and dayes? Euery man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth hym ſelf how longe he hath nede to faſt, &amp; what puniſhment he nedeth to tame hys fleſhe wythal. Therfor we do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe dayly faſtes as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eſſeyes dyd, nor yet with the makers of tradicions faſtes appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynted to a certen tyme: but we exhorte to contynuall ſoberneſſe, and to ſe that the fleſhe be brought vnder, leſt whan the Lorde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth we be found careleſſe without ony thought. And after thys maner alwayes we do exhorte, moue, and dryue, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon the church and congregacion of Chriſte, to a temperate lyfe, and to a faſte ſemynge a chriſten man, alwayes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge the lyberte of a chriſten man. But we do refuſe and caſt away, that fulbelly &amp; dronken faſt, as ſtynkynge hipocryſy the which we caſt in Gods teth, euen as a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and yet it maketh nothynge for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dwenge of the fleſhe, ſeynge that it beynge proude by the bodely exerciſe onelye regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth not true holyneſſe. I wyll ſende theſe hypocrites vnto Eſay the prophete to the .lviii. chap. were as they may learne ſufficy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently what maner of faſt God wold haue.
<pb facs="tcp:4840:32"/>
Thynk you (ſayeth he) that I loue thys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of faſtynge wherby men at preſcripte &amp; certayne dayes chaſten the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, goynge with theyr heades wrythen downe lyke an hoke, ſtrewed with aſſes, and clothed with ſackcloth? Wylt thou ſay that thys maner of faſt, and that vpon thys or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> appoynted day is more accepte to the Lord: but rather euen contrarywyſe, this maner of faſtynge do I alow &amp; loue: Forgeue thy dettres wrap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped in ſhrewed barganes, and lowſe theyr viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t oblygations, ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at lyberte whom thou dyddeſt caſt in pryſon for det, &amp; break from them all maner of bondes and yockes, diuyde out thy meat and drinke to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and thyrſty, and the port wayfarynge ſtraunger lede thou home to thy houſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſeyeſt the necked, clothe hym, &amp; turne not thy face from thyne owne fleſh. Here thou ſeyeſt that the body in dede muſt be chaſtyſed, but that outwarde puniſhement doth lytell auayle, excepte thou orden it to the faſtynge of the mynde, that is, to abſtayne from euell deſyres and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and frome couetouſneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercyfulneſſe. And that ye may faſt after thys wyſe, ye nede no choyce of meates excepte the manner or cauſe of tamynge
<pb facs="tcp:4840:33"/>
of the fleſh require it. For thou doſt abſteyn and vſeſt very ſkarſcely all maner of meat to the ſuſtenaunce of thy nature: therfore thou mayſt vſe fyſhe or fleſhe, whether thou wylt: how be it fyfſhesde a maner of fleſh as witneſſeth the Apoſtle .i. Corinth. xv. and Plini, in hys hyſtorye of nature: leſt ony playenge the Iew, ſhuld wrench hys noſe at thys.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of the difference of dayes, The newe learnynge.</head>
                  <p>The dayes be not equall and alyke, ſom be holy and ſo be not al, wherfore the ſonday is holy day to all chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men, to be halowed in ydelneſſe, lykewyſe oure ladyes dayes, &amp; the Apoſtelles dayes, &amp; other choſen of the church to kepe holy daye and to abſtayn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laboure ſo that yf ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ony ſeruyle or handy laboure, and worke in the afore ſayde dayes, he ſynneth. Wherfore yf ony man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrayned by neceſſite do ony worke, ether at home, or abrode on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy daye, he ſhalbe more cruelly handled of the byſhoppes, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciales, and curates, than yf he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted aduowtry, or had pylled his negboure with vſury.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learninge.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4840:33"/>
                  <p>Certayne dayes muſt be appoynted wher vpon men muſt forbeare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> handylaboure not that the daye ſhulde be holyer and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyer in the which we mete together, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the inordinate commynge together ſhulde not myniſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth in Chriſt. And that we maye heare the better and more commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, the worde of euerlaſtynge health, &amp; maye receaue the ſupper of the Lorde, and ſhewe to God with commune peticyon the neceſſite and nede of the church, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye praye together. Ther muſt nedes be certayne dayes appoynted in the whiche (whyle as the buſyneſſe of the ſoule is in hande) we muſt abſteyne from prophane &amp; houſholde labours. Yet for all that we muſt take hede leſt we leſe and deſtroye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les with ſnares of commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: and take hede that we playe not the Iewes and obſerue dayes, as they obſerued the ſabbath day, &amp; the feaſtes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new Moone, againſt the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt, (Gala. iiii.) as thoughe they were neceſſarye to be kepte for ryghteouſneſſe. For that were to caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the lyberte of fayth, &amp; to turne agayn to the weake and beggerly elementes and ceremonyes, and to denye Chriſte. The Hebrues were commaunded to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
<pb facs="tcp:4840:34"/>
daye, but whan the lyght came, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow vanyſhed awaye, ſo that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full now to ony man, to orden ony lawe, or make ſynne, where ſcripture maketh none, and leaueth the liberte. Colloſ. ii. Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge you in the parte of the Sabbath day &amp;c. Saynt Auſten ſpeaketh thus of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day in his boke of true innocency: Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yenge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kepynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabbath daye is ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken away, the which is ſhadowed by the va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon &amp; reſt of one daye, he kepeth a perpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall ſabbath daye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hauynge hope of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt to come, geueth hymſelfe to holy workes, &amp; doth not boaſt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his own workes, as though he had receaued them of none other, &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>legeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he worketh in hym, the which euen in workynge is quyet &amp; at reſte. Therfore ſaynt Ierome ſayeth very well, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe teſtament all dayes be equall, &amp; lyke holy, &amp; that euery day is the holy daye of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reccyon, &amp; that it is lawfull to faſt alwayes and to eate the body of the Lord, &amp; alwayes to praye. And the Apoſtell Roma. xiiii. wyll not that he ſhulde be raſhly iudged, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which iudgeth the ſame of euery day. Thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded or forbydden in the law, as concernynge dayes, meates, clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynges, places and perſones, or outwarde
<pb facs="tcp:4840:34"/>
thynges, they were ordened &amp; layd on mens neckes, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of correccyon: But now whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the goſpell doth ſhyne, they vanyſh awaye, and lyberte raigneth, where by we worſhip God nomore with certayne dayes prefixed, and with outwarde workes, as the Iewes dyd, but in ſprete and trueth. For theſe ceremonyes of the lawe dyd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe to the Iewes, and not to the gentyles Actu. xv. Ye maye ſe playnly. Mat. xii. Mar ii. Luce. xiiii. Ioh. v. and .ix. how that Chriſte the auctour of our lyberte, dyd intreate the Sabbath day. Therfore it were the byſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes dewty to put downe ſome of thoſe holy daies, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which chriſten people haue no nede of, the whiche geue occaſyon to the people, both to leſe theyr monye and theyr ſoules.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of prayer. The new learnynge.</head>
                  <p>We muſt praye at certayne houres, as at matynes, ſyxt houre, the thyrde, the fyrſt, at euenſonge and at ſuche other. And it is made more conueniently in churches halo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vnto God accordyng to this ſayenge: Bleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord in the churches. &amp;c. My houſe ſhalbe called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of prayer. Ther be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny thinges i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, which ſtire vp deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtned bels, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:35"/>
ſacrynge belles, ſyngynge, waxe, candels, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reliques of ſayntes, pictures, ymages, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed veſtimentes, the ſacrament of the al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tare, hallowed altares, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhip of ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, banners, ſupplications, the anoyntynge of the church, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hallowynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, the holy water, which euen the deuels be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed of, the preſence of angels, for it is wrytten Geneſis. xxviii. This place is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, and ther is a ſure promys of hearyng as it is in the thyrde boke of the kynges the viii. Chapter. The Lorde anſwered to the prayer of Salomon: I haue herde thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which thou prayed before me, I haue hal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed this place which thou haſte buylded, that I may ſet my name there for euermore and myne eyes and my harte ſhalbe there for euermore. &amp;c. Alſo ther be certayne hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed beedes, and they be honge vp on the churche dores, a certayne nombre of pater noſters and aues muſte be kepte, alſo ther be ſome prayers whiche haue pardon lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge therto. Alſo we muſte ſaye a pater noſter euery daye to oure owne Apoſtles, &amp; to the ſayntes whiche we haue choſen vnto our ſelues, for deuotion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4840:35"/>
                  <p>The bleſſed Trinite is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in euery place. Pſalm .c.iii. O thou my ſoule geue thankes and bleſſe the Lorde in euery place of his lordſhippe. Chriſte alſo ſayeth Ioh. iiii. The houre commeth &amp; now is, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the father in ſprete and in trueth: for verely ſuche the father requyreth to worſhippe hym. God is a ſprete, and they that worſhip hym, muſte worſhip hym in ſprete and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. Where as Chriſt doth anſwer the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritane, axynge hym of the place of pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, and ſayeth: Woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleue me, the houre commeth (yee, &amp; he ſayd that the houre was euen then) when ye ſhal nother in this mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne, nor yet in Ieruſalem worſhip the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther .i. Timo. ii. ſayeth Paul: I wyl that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praye in euery place lyftynge pure &amp; cleane ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, without wrath, arguynge or alterca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon. Lykewyſe in the .vii. chapter of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes where ſaynt Steuen checkynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blynd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of the Iewes, auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cynge the temple of Salomon, ſayeth: But he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is hyeſt of al dwelleth not in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples made with handes.</p>
                  <p>As ſayeth alſo the prophete Eſay .lxvi. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is my ſeate &amp; earth is my foote ſtoole, what houſe wyll ye buylde for me ſayeth the Lorde? or what is my reſtynge place? hath
<pb facs="tcp:4840:36"/>
not my hande made all theſe thynges? and all theſe thynges be made ſayeth the Lorde. On whom than ſhall I loke? euen hym that is of an humble &amp; a lowly ſprete, ſtandeth in awe of my wordes. We haue the wordes of the father, &amp; of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, &amp; of the place of prayer, the which the holy gooſt ſpake, ſhall we not beleue the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne whom the father co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be herde? Mat. xvii. And he dyd ſaye with an earneſt affirmacyon: Woman beleue me. &amp;c. I knowe that ther was in the olde law the arke of the conuenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and the ſumptuous temple of the Lorde, where as the Iewes had the promyſe of God .ii. Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra. vii. Myne eares ſhalbe lyfted vp vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares of him which ſhal praye in this place for I haue choſen this place. But what ſhal we do now? ſeynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Moſes is gone, which was the ſeruaunt of the whole houſe of the Lorde, &amp; the ſonne commeth Ieſus Chriſt whiche is the Apoſtle and the byſhop of our fayth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Heb. iii. &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is com to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quyck te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of God, as a byſhop of good thynges for to come, entrynge by a greater &amp; more ꝑfect tabernacle, not made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay) not as ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s buyldynge, nother by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of goates &amp; calues, but by his own bloud he entred once for al i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:4840:36"/>
place, &amp; fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de euerlaſtyng rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption. Heb ix. He is gone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gaue the lawe, &amp; an other is come in his rowme, by whom grace is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioh. i. Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is gone, for the true preſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order of Melchiſedech is come. To conclude, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fygure is vanyſhed, becauſe the lyght hath ſhyned. Then what nede we ſo coſtly &amp; gloryous pompe of ceremonies in the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? we diſprayſe not thoſe buyldinges, to the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to hear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modiouſly: but we diſprayſe the abuſe &amp; the erroure, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they kepe no meaſure, &amp; can neuer make an ende of buyldynge &amp; deckynge of ſuch royal churches. Exo. xxxvi. at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of Moſes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cryer forbyddeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld offer vp ony more to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buyldyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tabernacle: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people offred vp a great deale more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nede was. Now our cryers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ende &amp; meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre gyftes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buyldinges of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples. Wher doth Chriſt requyre in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtament ſuch orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of churches? and where doth he appoynt ſuch buyldyng to be made? Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded not he vs to worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpret &amp; in verite? The which two wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole tragedy of ceremonies, which we thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke profitable &amp; good for praier.
<pb facs="tcp:4840:37"/>
For what helpeth to the ſprete and trueth of worſhippyng of God, ſuch infinite diuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſite of veſtimentes, belles, organes, and ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of dyuerſe kyndes? Yf thoſe thynges kyndle deuotion, &amp; ſteare vp a mans mynde to God, it were beſt that not only churches but alſo houſes, townes, hye waies &amp; ſtretes ſhuld be ful of yanglyng of belles, &amp; be reple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhed with ymages. The Lorde requyreth the ſprete and trueth, and we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye wyſe ſhewe and ſet forth a carnal pompe, &amp; ſolem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite of ceremonyes, the which is not only as great as all the Iewes faſhions and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, but paſſeth them farre, both in nombre and greatneſſe, hauyng in ſteade of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprete the fleſh: for the trueth, mooſt coloured and paynted ypocryſye: for we ſpende the whole daye with ſyngynge, ſacrifyſyng and mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blynge. We ſpeake with tunges, but no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preacheth, which ſhulde ſpeake vnto men, to edifye, exorte, and to comforte .i. Cor. xiiii. The Apoſtle wyl leuer ſpeake .v. wordes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may iuſtruc &amp; teach other alſo, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ten thouſand w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges. We tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre out pſalmes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng for auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage &amp; lucre, makyng a ſound w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; alas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to geue place to this blind ſeruice, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:4840:37"/>
of the apoſtle alſo. We crye now a dayes as the Iewes cryed in tymes paſte: Ieremie. vii. The temple of the Lorde, the temple of the Lorde, the temple of the Lorde, Goddes ſeruice, Goddes ſeruice, Goddes ſeruice, truſtyng in wordes of lyenge: where as all thys buſyneſſe of ceremonyes, is playne hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red geare for mony, that it may be fulfilled, that the Lorde ſayde. Malachie. i. Who is ther amonge you that wyll ſhut the dores, &amp; wyl kyndle myn aultare frely for nought? wherfore it foloweth, I haue no pleaſure in you ſayth the Lorde of hooſtes, I wyll take no reward of your handes. Yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the tragedy and ſpectakle of ceremonyes lyketh you ſo well, go to, let vs brynge home agayne the whole Iewyſneſh, and the whole maner of worſhyppynge of the Iewes, let vs deck vp Aaron, let vs orden leuytes, let vs kyll and offer vp ſhepe, oxen, and calues: and euen let vs be circumcyſed wyth the madde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, and let vs loke for an other Meſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, that may bryng vs in to the lande of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan: not by the power of the Lorde, but of the world. Surely yf that mooſt coſtly and ſumptuous worſhyppyng of God is chriſtes religion, in the which holyneſſe conſiſteth, I graunt that I can not tell what is oure
<pb facs="tcp:4840:38"/>
religion. But yf Chriſt be oure Lorde and maſter, and hys doctryne be the doctryne of the father, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe and the waye, then is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole heape of ceremonyes nothynge leſſe, than the worſhyppyng of God. Where do we reade in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel of hyred prayers which ye wyll let a man haue for mony, and yf he geue no penny, he ſhall haue no pater noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? where doth the Lorde alowe byenge &amp; ſellyng, choppynge and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gynge in holy thynges? As for thoſe places which they brynge for the appoyntynge and aſſignynge of a certayne place of prayer, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſe that they handle them without ony ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of iudgement, and with playne ygno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of ſcriptur. It is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame ſorte that they fayne, that the deuyl is afrayed of holy water, as thoughe he were not more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed at the ſyght of a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, whome the oyntement of the holy gooſt, hath made holy, and is the temple of the holy gooſt?</p>
                  <p>And as for that, thay they brynge for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge of beedes, and the nombre of pater noſters, and the Pſalter of our lady &amp; ſuche other, it is more vayne, then ony tryfles be in the worlde, and more foolyſher then the tales which olde wyues tell in wynter nyghtes by the fyre ſyde. Therfore we muſt
<pb facs="tcp:4840:38"/>
praye to the father of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorowe oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte in ſpirit and truthe in euery place, that our prayers be not bound to places. For ether we go in to oure preuy chambre and ſhut the dore after vs, &amp; pray vnto the father, which is in ſecrete: or we praye in euery place after the learnynge of ſaynt Paule, in the fyrſt epiſtel the .ii. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Timoth. For the whole worlde is the temple &amp; churche of God. The heauen &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauen of al heauens ar not able to receaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, how much leſſe then thys church? Yf I aſcende vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (ſayeth the royal pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete) thou arte ther: yf I deſcende and go downe to hel, thou art preſent. And God his owne ſelf ſayeth by Ieremy the prophete in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxiii. chapt. I fyl both heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth. And the Apoſtell in his preachyng to the men of Athens, ſayeth: God is not far from vs, for we lyue in hym, are moued, and be in hym. Actu. xvii.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of vowes, The newe learnynge,</head>
                  <p>Vowe to the Lorde &amp; perfourme it that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye vowe Pſal. lxxv. Therfor we may vowe &amp; we ought to geue it that we vowe: for ther a is lawe made of geuynge to them whiche vowed. In the .iiii. boke of the ſentence it is wrytten. A vowe is made when a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his
<pb facs="tcp:4840:39"/>
owne wyl promyſeth that he wyl do or kepe ſome good thynge, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which otherwyſe he is not bound, although he be bound after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vowe be made. There be .iii. principalle &amp; ſubſtancial vowes, that is: of pouerte cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtite &amp; obedience. He that is once made a re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligious man or a preſte, is bound to lyue ſo for euer, by hys vowe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>A vowe is a law (ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcoole me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) made to perfourme ſuch thynges as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue vowed It is playne what the holy ſcripture doth af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrme and iudge of the lawe, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of it. Now is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not iuſtifyed, or made righteous by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe and workes of Moſes lawe: how muche leſſe by the worke of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, whan as ſcripture vtterly refuſeth and defyeth all mans traditions, and God wyll not be worſhypped with lawes of mans tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicions, Eſay. xxix. Math. xv. Marc. vii. For onely fayth in Chriſte doth iuſtifye and not workes what ſo euer they be, and ſyncere fayth wyll not ſuffer men to put confidence in theyr workes. In dede fayth bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth forth workes becauſe ſhe worketh by charite, but ſhe ſuffereth no man to truſt vnto them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys vngodly opinion, that he ſhuld be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed
<pb facs="tcp:4840:39"/>
by them, becauſe that were to deny the Lord y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bought vs with hys precious bloud. Vowes are wont to be taken with none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opinion, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that by them ſynnes ſhuld be done away, and to deſerue grace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes: therefore they ſpring of the ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſtes religion, &amp; they be playnely wicked &amp; therfor they be nought and of no pryce. For euen the ſcoole me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay, that thoſe thynges be no vowes, which do turne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage or hynderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſaluation: ſeyng that a vowe hathe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thynges folowynge, which an oth hathe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is: iuſtice, iudgement &amp; truthe. To wyll &amp; deſyre to be iuſtifyed by workes, is to caſt away the grace of Chriſt: and that is to leſe the true healthe and ſaluacion. Therfore theſe vowes that be ſo greatly boaſted of, be no vowes, and of no value, for thys ſhort ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gument of Paule fearfull to all vowers ſhall ſtande: yf ryghteouſneſſe be of the law, then Chryſt dyed in vayne. Galat. v. Ye are gone quyte from Chriſt as many as are iuſtifyed by the lawe, and are falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce Gala. ii. We know that a man is not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed by the workes of the law, but by the fayth of Ieſu Chriſte. Yf theſe thynges be ſayde vnto the Iewes, the which preſumed
<pb facs="tcp:4840:40"/>
to be iuſtifyed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of moſes law, who can abyde our vngodlyneſſe, which loke for thoſe thynges by the workes of our lawes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which onely Chriſt geueth in fayth? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it repenteth vs of oure rechleſſe vowe, &amp; we deſyre forgeueneſſe of God, for our ſyn done by oure folyſh vowe, &amp; we turne agayn to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyberte, which Chriſtes bloude gat vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs with a ſure belefe, and defyenge the maſters &amp; teachers of workes, the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of Chriſte, &amp; we rather heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt: Gala. v. Stande in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyberte where with Chriſt hath made vs fre, &amp; wrap not your ſelues agayn in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yock of bondage. As touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places, which they bring owt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old teſtament for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayntaynyng and ſtablyſſynge of vowes, they make nothynge for the purpoſe: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of vowyng per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, &amp; now be put away as be ſacrifices. Actu. xv. Fayth in Chriſte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all outwarde thynges fre: nother doth the bondage of vowes, and our lyberte agre. What nede many wordes? Oure vowes be without faythe, &amp; therfore they be ſyn. Now who wold be afrayed to leaue &amp; forſake ſyn?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of counſels, the newe learnynge.</head>
                  <p>The goſpell is diuyded into counſels and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes, we be bound to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes
<pb facs="tcp:4840:40"/>
&amp; not to deſpyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſels. The counſelles be in &amp; .v. of Math. to loue our enemyes, not to reſiſt euell, not to ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in the court or law, to lende euery one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nedeth, &amp; ſuch other lyke. The wich yf they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, they were to heuy burthens for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new lawe. Thus ſaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>We haue a counſel in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel of lyuyng ſyngle Math. xix. &amp; .i. Corint. vii. But they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyfte of Math. they be no counſelles but preceptes: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thynge is manyfeſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> text. For Chriſt dothe threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he wolde not haue done, yf he had onely cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelled. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth threaten a payn, doth propound &amp; ſet forth, a law, &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelleth not. Moreouer it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: Loue thy neyghboure as thy ſelfe. That loue con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyneth in it thoſe thinges, which we haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of. And alſo luſt is forbydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; therfore be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aforeſayd forbydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mat. he had re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hearſed thoſe thynges which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcoolme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels, ſayeth by &amp; by after: That ye may be the chyldren of youre father whiche is in heauen. Math. v. Lykewyſe alſo ſaynt Luke (after that he had rekened vp theſe lawes) ſayeth: And ye ſhal be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonnes of the mooſte hyeſt. Therfore they that do them not, ſhall not be the chyldren. Surely a
<pb facs="tcp:4840:41"/>
counſell her wolde not haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this maner yee thus dyd Chriſoſtom. Auſten, Hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lary vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of Chriſte. Then yf the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded all thoſe thynges, why do we that be ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, louſe and &amp; breake the lawes of the Lord for oure pleaſure?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of matrymony. The newe learnynge.</head>
                  <p>The fourthe degre of kynred ſtoppeth matrimony. There be .xii. impedimentes of matrymony, which hinder maryage to be made, and loſe it yf it be contract, namely, errour, condition, vowe, kynred, faute or cryme, the diuerſite of worſhippyng, power bond, honeſty, yf thou be of affynite, yf thou be impotent in rendrynge dutye. Theſe hynder mariage to be made, &amp; yf it be made breake it agayne. Certayne thynges ther be which hyndre mariage to be made, but they loſe it not yf it be contract: that is the tyme of not ſpouſynge, and the forbyddyng of the churche. Alſo a ſpirituall kynred is gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſacrament of baptyme &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation or byſhoppynge the which letteth matrymony to be, and putteth a ſunder it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is made. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the order of ſubdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, deacon, and preſthod ſtop matrymony to be taken, and putte it
<pb facs="tcp:4840:41"/>
awaye yf it is taken, bycauſe that the vowe of chaſtite is ioyned to thoſe orders. Alſo yf ther be a deuorcement, both the man and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman muſt abyde vnmaryed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Ther be degrees of kynne or conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinite and affinite red to be forbydden in the .xviii. of Leuiticus, namely: father, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſtepmother, a natural ſyſter, lawful ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter both of father and mother, coſyn, au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers ſyde &amp; of the mothers ſyde, the wyfe of myne vncle, the doughter in lawe, the wyfe of my brother, ſtepdoughter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtepſon or ſtepdoughter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyſter of my wyfe my wyfe beynge alyue. Here is forbyd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt degre of affinite, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of kyne or conſanguinite: thoughe the doughter or nefe of my brother or ſyſter is not rekened to be forbydden. Seyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe be prouyded &amp; taken hede of, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God, they muſt nedes be honeſt, ſo that it were folyſh hardy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe for a man put his decrees, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God. Thoſe thynges that be ſpoken of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tymes that be voyde of ſpouſels, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byddynge of the churche, they be mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencyons. And the ſpirituall kynred hath no teſtimony in the ſcripture. Therfore yf
<pb facs="tcp:4840:42"/>
it ſhyne and glyſter wyth neuer ſo fare and goodly a lykeneſſe, we maye as eaſely deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe it, as receaue it. Why doth not holy fra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternite let mariage, by the which we are all knyt together in Chriſte? They be my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and my ſyſters as manye as confeſſe Chriſt. That the order is a let vnto matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, it is nothynge els but fals ſpeakynge throughe hypocryſye: for yf matrimony be a ſacrament, (as they ſay) I can not ſe, why holy order can not ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holyneſſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony. Mariage is honourable, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt wytneſſeth Heb. xiii. And they thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holyneſſe of matrimony is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the holyneſſe of order, the which thynge the Apoſtle neuer knewe .i. Timo. iii. Tit. i. Where he wyll that a byſhoppe ſhulde be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſbande of one wyfe: and .ii. Timo. iiii. He calleth it the learnyng of deuels yf ony man forbyddeth matrimony .i. Corin. vii. He ſayeth not onely it is better to mary the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to burne: but he commaundeth openly in this maner: For the auoydyng of fornicacyon, let euery man haue his wyfe. Who is that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? is it not manyfeſt that mariage is fre to all men which haue not the gyft of chaſtite? Saynt Ierome ſheweth a cauſe, why in the .ix. of the Actes. Chriſt called S.
<pb facs="tcp:4840:42"/>
Paule a choſen veſſell: namely, becauſe he was the ſtorehouſe of the lawe and of the holy ſcripture. And againſt Iouinian he ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth: I wyll brynge forth Paule the Apoſtle, whom as ofte as I reade, I thynke that I heare not wordes, but tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deryng. But they which defende the fylthy ſyngle lyuynge, deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſe this thonderynge of this choſen veſſel, as the barkyng of a dogge, &amp; they thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is within orders, ſynneth deadly yf he mary a wyfe. God the father dyd orden ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riage, the ſonne dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende and honoure it with his preſence and with his fyrſt myra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle, the holy gooſt pronounced it honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Paule the ſeruaunt of Ieſu Chriſt for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byddeth not biſſhoppes and deacons to be maryed: And they which boaſt them of the Goſpell, nombre the mariage of preſtes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge deadly ſinnes, as a prophane and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holy thynge, the which the holyneſſe of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der can not ſuffer. Why beleue they not at the leaſte the ſentence of holy fathers? for Theophilactus vpon the .viii. Chapter of Mathew ſayeth: Learne here that mariage hyndereth not a man from vertue, for the prynce of the Apoſtles hadde a mother in lawe. Farthermore we do alowe no deuorcement, but in caſe of fornicacion,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:43"/>
as Chriſte ſayeth Math. xix. where as it is lawful for the vngylty after the deuorceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to mary agayn: the which thynge myght be eaſely done yf the man aduouterer or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man ſhulde be kylled, after the law of God Deute. xxxii. Now they tary both vnmaried the which is a deuorcement rather in name and in worde then in dede. The texte of Math. xix. is manyfeſt: (Whoſoeuer forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his wyfe, but only for fornication and maryeth an other, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth aduoutry.</p>
                  <p>For this clauſe that is put betwene: (except it be for fornicacyon) declareth &amp; ruleth the whole ſentence, that yf ony fornicacyon do chaunce in the meane ſeaſon, he that forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the woman aduouterer and maryeth an other, he beynge vngylty, that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted none aduoutry. And why do not we in ſuch caſes, go rather to the ſcripture, that is inſpyred of God, then to thoſe wryters of ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes? ſeynge that the Apoſtle .ii. to Tim. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iii. Chapter pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth and ſayeth that the ſcripture is profytable for correccyon and teachynge.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of Byſſhoppes. The new learyng.</head>
                  <p>A Byſhop is of hyer authorite then a ſymple preſt, and hath the reſeruacyon and kepynge behynde to hym of certayne cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:
<pb facs="tcp:4840:43"/>
for the hyer that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degre is, the greater and more is the power. And this new lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge wynketh at and ouerſeeth the po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe &amp; pryde more then worldly, of them which cal themſelues the ſucceſſours of the Apoſtles and preach not the word of God, the which is the mooſt worthy hye office in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>When ther roſe a contention amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſciples, which of them ſhuld be thought greateſt amonge them, Chriſt ſayd: The lordes of the gentyles haue domination o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, but it ſhal not be ſo amonge you. Where as Chriſt wolde haue taken cleane out of the diſciples myndes the deſyre of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure. For yf oure Lorde and mayſter dyd not come to be myniſtred to, but to myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and ſerue other (as it is Math. xx.) how muche leſſe ſhall it become ſeruauntes, to ſwell and be proude with worldly deſyre of honoure? The which thynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth playnly. i. Cor. iiii. So (ſayeth he) let a man reken vs, as myniſters and ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and diſpoſers of the ſecretes of God: he ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth myniſters and ſeruauntes, and not lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and prynces of the worlde. So in many places of his epyſtles, he calleth hymſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:4840:44"/>
This place (ſayeth he) maketh agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which do geue themſelues to ſloggyſneſſe, ydelneſſe, and to ſlepe, &amp; thinke that it is an offence, yf they reade ſcripture: and deſpyſe them as bablers and vnprofitable, which ar occupyed in the lawe of the Lorde both day and nyght, not takynge hede, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded euen learnyng alſo after the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hearſynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſacyon of a byſhoppe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>¶ Of Ceremonyes.</head>
               <p>Men reken that ceremonyes haue the name of a towne in Tuſcia called Cerete, and by ceremonyes we meane the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pynge of God, but outwardly.</p>
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The new learnynge.</head>
                  <p>The ceremonyes which our fathers or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dened, muſt be kepte, and not chaunged, the which are worſhippynge of god. For the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligious men, and rude preſtes do defende the ceremonyes (what ſo euer they be) ſo ſtyfly, as thoughe holyneſſe conſyſted and ſtode in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only. For we haue ſene in theſe tymes, the holy orders contende and ſtryue wyth vnſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheable hatred amonge them ſelues for ceremonyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4840:44"/>
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>We may not ſwarue nother to the ryght hand, nor to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lefte hand, but we muſt walk in the kynges hye way. Our lyfe is in that caſe, thal we can not be without ceremony<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es. For we be not angelical ſpirites, but me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; as long as we lyue in thys vyſyble world, in the preſon of thys body, we muſt nedes haue difference of workes, of places, of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, of tymes, of perſones, &amp; of other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. For we be (as the Apoſtell ſayeth. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano. xii.) many membres, and one body, &amp; not hauynge all one acte or office. But after that the lyght of the goſpell came, and folowed the ſhadow of the law we ſhuld vſe very few ceremonyes, as we haue baptyme and the ſupper of the Lorde, after the ordina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unce of Chriſt in the newe teſtament. For we vſe (as we be alwayes redy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſte) to ſet muche by ceremonyes, and to concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a vayne opinion and confidence to be iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtifyed by them, yf they be perfectly done: &amp; yf we leaue them vndone, we conceaue a folyſh feare, (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is) of euery hande a noughty conſcience. Therfore leſt we ſhuld ſwarue away from the pryke of trew holyneſſe, let vs take fayth and charite vnto vs, as the
<pb facs="tcp:4840:45"/>
rulers and gyders of ceremonyes, in the whiche yf they were done, they myght be done godly. Before all thynges we muſte take great hyde and diligent prouiſion, leſt ceremonyes hurte and deſtroye the head &amp; the roote of oure religion, which is fayth in Chriſt. Fayth and belefe in Chriſt is onely our ryghteouſneſſe, which worketh after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by charite, the which yf it continue in ſafegarde in the liberte of the ſprite, ye may lyue and be occupyed in the ceremonyes of the churche without ony blame. For he that is iuſtifyed, by faythe, kepeth ceremonyes, leſt he ſhuld offende thoſe that be yet weake in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth, not as neceſſary to ryghteouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, but as a teachyng and a bryngyng vp for weaklynges: beleuyng ſtedfaſtly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thoſe outward thynges be fre vnto vs thorow fayth, and that we owe nothyng to ony body but onely loue. Roma. xiii. By thys rule the Apoſtle beynge conuerſant amonge hys brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without the yeoperde and the loſſe of conſcience and faythe, was ſo fre by the ſprite of faythe, that for al that he made hym ſelfe an vnderlynge and a ſeruaunt of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and was of all faſhion, to ſaue ſome at the leeſt. He had knowlege, but he knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowlege dyd ſwell, and charite dyd edyfye.
<pb facs="tcp:4840:45"/>
i. Corinth. viii. and .ix. He graunted that all thynges be lawfull vnto hym, but that all thynges be nor profitable, that al thynges be lawfull, but all thynges do not edifye. And he dyd folowe thoſe thynges which belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vnto peace, and to edifyenge. We wyll folow thys Apoſtle not geuynge oure lyber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te to the occaſion of the fleſhe, but in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge one an other by charite. Galat. v.</p>
                  <p>Here muſt the ouerſeers and miniſters of the churche be monyſhed, that they vnlade the congregacion, holden downe with ſo many ceremonyes and lawes, that almooſt the condicion and ſtate of the Iewes were more tollerable, then the ſtate of Chriſten men. Now, it is not onely folyſheneſſe, but alſo wyckedneſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ſtryue amonge them ſelfes for ceremonyes (I can not tel what) whoſe bage is, charite, and not ceremonyes. Ihon. xiii.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of mans tradicions. The newe learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Ther is a canon or a rule, the whiche maketh equall the conſtitucions of popes and byſſhoppes wyth the goſpell, and it affirmeth that the goſpell can not be well
<pb facs="tcp:4840:46"/>
vpholde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excepte the ſtatutes and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the fathers be kepte, as Leo the .iiii. ſayeth in the .xx. diſtinction in the chapter. De libellis. All thynges that be neceſſary to be knowen to our ſaluation, be not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the canonicall ſcripture, but the holy gooſt afterwarde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſcripture was wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dyd ſhew many wholſome thynges vnto oure forefathers. Iohan. xvi. I haue many thynges to ſay vnto you, which ye can not beare at thys tyme. And thoſe thynges that were in practyſe than, are not now all writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, but euen geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from one to an other as by hande, and are come euen to oure tyme, as Damaſcen in a ſermon of the dead wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that the memory of faythfull deadmen came vnto vs from the Apoſtels tymes.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer Paule taught the people, that he purchaſſed vnto Chriſte, whan he was with them many thynges the which were neuer wrytten. Alſo he that heareth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church let hym be counted as an heythen &amp; a publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane therfor ſhe may make lawes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucions neceſſary for mans ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo that is neceſſary to ſaluation, whoſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſyon is deadly ſynne, but the ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the church be ſuch, the fyrſt is proued by Abbas in the proemy or preface of the
<pb facs="tcp:4840:46"/>
decretales. And in the fyrſt chapter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucions, he allegeth Calderine, Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drea and Thomas. And for thys purpoſe maketh the text in the chapter. Quo iure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viii. diſtinction. where as it is wrytten y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the breaker of the tradicions of the churche ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth deadly, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alſo the poſitiue lawe byndeth in matters of conſcience, ergo they bynd. Herevpon Iohan Mayre with great pryde &amp; diſdayne ſayeth in the .iiii. diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .iii. q. To thynke that he that breaketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaundementes of the church ſynneth not deadly, is an erroure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Mathew the .xvii. Chapter the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father maketh his onely begotten ſonne doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor and teacher of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, ſayenge: Heare hym. And he put his wordes in his mouthe. Deuteronomy .xviii. he ſayeth: And I wyll be a reuenger and a punyſſher of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which refuſe the learnynge of thys doctoure. He which ſayeth Iohan. vii. My doctryne is not myne, but his, which ſent me, that doctor is the euerlaſtynge wyſdome of the father, the way, the lyght, the truthe, whom we beleue ſtedſtly that he bothe wolde and dyd geue
<pb facs="tcp:4840:47"/>
vnto his church, not botched, clowted, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfecte and vnſtable learnynge, but ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, perfecte, and vnchaungeable, to the whiche nedeth nothyng to be put to, as an addition: for thoſe thynges that are neceſſary for to be knowen for mans ſaluation, be contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned plenteouſly in the canonical ſcripture. Somtymes the Apoſtles ſpake and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon the kyngdome of God, more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly in ſpeakynge, than it is wrytten in bokes, yet for all that, as for the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the ſentence and doctrine, they preached none other thynge, than the goſpell, whiche we haue wrytten: ſo that thoſe thynges which perteyne vnto a chriſten mans lyfe, muſte be learned of no where els, but of the byble, that is of the newe teſtement and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde. For all ſcripture, geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the inſpiration of God (ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle .ii. tim .iii.) is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to teachynge, to improue, to informe, &amp; to inſtruc in righteouſneſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the man of God may be perfecte and prepared to all good workes. Then why do we thruſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches handes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of men, as neceſſary to Chriſtes regilion? I do not ſpeake here of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ciuyll lawe, I know that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of ſecular power are to be kepte for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſcience ſake: for they haue theyr ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of Goddes lawe.
<pb facs="tcp:4840:47"/>
Rom. xiii. I ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> decrees of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with the which they wolde bynde mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. Farthermore the Apoſtle in the .ii. Tim iii. chap. prayſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a great verdit &amp; prayſe ſayenge:, The holy ſcripture may make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe vnto health thorow fayth which is in Chriſt Ieſu. Who dar ſet thys tytle before his conſtitucions, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they maye make you learned to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? thys honour is onely dew vnto the holy ſcriptur of God. Farther more, yf ther were ony thynges ſhewed oure fathers a. M. year ago by the holy gooſt, the which were not knowen (in tyme of the flourynge of the churche, that newly dyd ſpringe vp) to the Apoſtles and to the church, they be ether neceſſary to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, or not neceſſary. Yf they be not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, but ordened for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme, why is a mans conſcience bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with them? Yf they be neceſſary, ether ther is an other waye to ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacion nowe, than was in the primitiue churche, or els they were all damned that departed before that reuelation: for they knewe not the thynge that was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to theyr ſaluacion. The whyche thynges, ſeynge that they be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt vayne that can be and foolyſh, and that the ſame maner of iuſtifyenge and ſaluation is now,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:48"/>
that was than, and was than, that is now: why make we thoſe thynges neceſſary, that be not neceſſary? And why ſet we ſo lytell by the lyberte of the goſpell that we had as leue our dreames, as the mooſt holy goſpel? we do not reiect and refuſe the conſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and ordinaunces of byſſhoppes, which vexe not the conſcience, but pertayne and be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytable for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune peace and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite of mens conuerſacion: onely we defy &amp; reiecte thoſe lawes, in the which ether they commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de or forbidde vnder payn of deadly ſynne, without the lawe of God. Onely god ought to raygne in the conſcience, in whoſe hande peculyarly be menes ſoules. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calleth hym the aduerſary of God, which goeth aboute to ſyt in the temple of God, and boaſte hym ſelf as a God .ii. Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalo. ii. And .ii. Cori. iii. We be the miniſters of the new teſtament, miniſters of the ſprit and not of the letter. What auayle mans conſtitutions to iuſtificacion yf ye ſay that they prepare to obey God the eaſyer? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: There is nothyng that can prepare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God or faſhion it but onely the grace of God. The Apoſtle Galat. i. pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth acurſed, not onely ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo an angell of heauen, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> durſt preach
<pb facs="tcp:4840:48"/>
an other goſpell then Paule preached. Yf it be the power of God to ſaluacyon, of all that beleue, why do we myngle and ioyne our chaffe with ſo great a power? And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt to the Corinthians the thyrde chapter: Other fundacyon can no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay, then that which is layed, which is Ieſus Chriſt. Yf no man ought to put ony thyng to Moſes law Deute. xii. why ſhulde we adde &amp; put vnto the goſpell ony thyng? ſeynge euen Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racenſis a ſcooleman, calleth it the mooſt perfect lawe and ryghteſt, and the ſtraygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in preceptes. Why do we not leaue our lawes, and follow the buſyneſſe that Chriſt appoynted, Math. the laſt: Teache all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to kepe all thynges what ſo euer I haue commaunded you? We be myniſters &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of Chriſte, and diſpoſers of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes of God. Now is it requyred of the ſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes or diſpoſers that they be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full. Theſe priuities and myſteries be the artycles of oure fayth of the Goſpell, the wyſedome of the croſſe, the knowlege of grace gotten by Chriſte: Let vs preache theſe thynges for the health of the people of God, and let vs not abuſe oure power the which the Lorde gaue vs to edifye with, and not to deſtroye .ii. Corinth. the .xiii. cha,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:49"/>
The Canon or rule that maketh the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of fathers equale with the Goſpel, is openly vngodly and wycked, the whiche euen oure aduerſaryes can not receaue, yf they knewe the canon of the ſcripture. To be ſhorte, fayth where with a ryghteous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyueth is conceaued, taken, and drawen out of the canonicall ſcripture, and not of the decrees of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers, as ſaynt Auſtyne wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſeth, in the .ix. boke of the cytie of God the .xviii. Chapter. Then wherefore ſhulde I receaue it as an artycle of my fayth, that whiche the ſcripture inſpired of God hath not? I am commaunded to proue and trye ſpretes whether they be of God or no: the which lyberte of iudgynge of all doctrines by the ſcriptures, no man wyll take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. The wordes of ſaint Ihon in the .xvi. Chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſtablyſh nothynge mans tradityons: for God dyd fulfyl his promeſſe at Wytſonday when he ſent the holy gooſt, and led his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyples in to all trueth: the whiche before that tyme they coulde not beare. Who wyl denye that the memorye and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of thoſe that be departed dyd come from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles vnto vs, ſeynge that ſaynt Paule the fyrſte to the Teſſalonians the fourth chapter commaunded the Teſſalonians,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:49"/>
that one ſhulde comforte another, with the worde of the reſurreccyon of the dead in Chriſte? But now that we maye anſwer to theyr rethoricall argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where in they reaſon, that by the breakynge of the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the church, a man ſynneth dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we anſwere: that the knowlege of ſynne is by the the lawe. Roma. the .iii. Chapter. The Apoſtle ſpeaketh of Goddes lawe, and not of mans. Alwayes vnderſtande I of mans lawe that is clere or whole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s law, the which aſſayeth to binde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; I moued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience nother ought, nor can be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with mans conſtitucyon: for we are indued with lyberte which we wyll vſe, the which lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te is the lyberte of the conſcyence .i. Corin. the .iii. Chapter. All thynges be yours, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it be Paul, ether Apollo, ether Cephas wherby we vnderſtande that nother Paul, nor Cephas hath authorite to bynde mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, where God doth not bynde. The fyrſt to the Corinthians the twelft Chapter Be ye not made ſeruauntes of men. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſenſes the ſeconde Chapter. You beynge dead wyth Chriſte, why be ye holden ſtyl wyth decrees? And for the mooſt parte ſuche conſtitucyons be contrarye to the worde &amp; dede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles. But as Gerſon
<pb facs="tcp:4840:50"/>
beareth wytneſſe in the ſeconde lection of the ſpirituall lyfe the .vii. corollary: It is not in the popes power, nother in the councels power, nor in the churches power to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the learnynge geuen and taught of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geliſtes and of Paule: Maſter Gaſper Satzger dyd ſe this in the defenſion of the conſtitucyons of the churche, the which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly and playnly graunteth: that the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge that is without the ſcripture, though it be good, yet byndeth not by goddes lawe. And it is no maruayl, for only Chriſt ought to raygne in mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience by his worde, which onely maye ſaue and condempne.</p>
                  <p>Math. the .x. Chapter. Feare not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which can kyll the body and not the ſoule, but fear hym which can caſt both body and ſoule in euerlaſtyng fyre. Truely yf they can make a conſtitucyon and commaunde it vnder payne of deadly ſynne, they maye kyll the ſoule, but the trueth of the goſpell is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe. The ſentence of Ezechiell is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced agaynſt them in the .xiii. Chapter: Wo be to them that make bolſters vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heade of euery age, to catch ſoules y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might kyl ſoules which dye not. How doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcooleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s learnyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of byndyng of mens conſtitucyons agre with it ſelfe?
<pb facs="tcp:4840:50"/>
ſeynge Thomas graunteth playnly, that the commaundementes of the poſitiue law bynde more with the intent of the lawma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, then with the wordes of it: ſo that he is more to be rekened a breaker of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement that doth agaynſt the intent of the lawmaker, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwarueth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the letter of the ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maker of the poſitiue lawe is not, that hys precepte ſhulde be alwayes kepte, becauſe that many impedimentes may chaunce in the which it is not expedient to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, yee ſomtyme the kepynge of the precepte were damnable. Wherfore in euery precept of the poſitiue lawe, the excepcyon of a rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable cauſe is admitted. Now put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is a law y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal not eat fleſh on the fryday, &amp; that a preſte ſhal not haue a wyfe. Here the intent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawmaker is to brynge to goodneſſe. But it chaunceth yf we kepe thoſe lawes, that ether the lyberte of a chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten man be in ieopardy, or we offende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Goddes lawe. In this caſe the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitiue lawe byndeth not, for the intent of the lawmaker is not to kyll ony man, or to geue an occaſyon to breake Goddes lawe. But ſeynge that it can not be ſatiſfyed and fulfylled, doutleſſe it remitteth and lowſeth
<pb facs="tcp:4840:51"/>
thoſe thynges that it dyd decre. And yf ther chaunce ony reaſonable cauſe of breakynge ſuch a tradicyon, it wyl pronounce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſour aſſoyled and cleare and not raſhe: but what more reaſonable cauſe is ther, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auoydynge of deadly ſynne, or the ieopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of conſcience? Paule was content ſo to chaſtiſe his fleſh (to auoyde offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng of his brother), that he wolde neuer eate fleſh ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to offende hym.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <div n="new" type="teaching">
                  <head>¶ Of Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels and lawes made by a great multytude of byſhoppes gathered together. The new learnyng.</head>
                  <p>Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authorite of councels be deſpiſed, all thynges in the churche ſhalbe doutfull &amp; vncertayne, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hereſyes that were once condemned in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels ſhal come agayn. Therfore it is not lawfull vnto a priuate man to affyrme or teache ony thynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the councels. For the councell is gathered together in the name of Chriſt, it is ruled of the holy gooſte, and therfore it erreth not, ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyons of the councels be the conſtitucyons of the catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke church, whom the councell doth repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. But thoſe thynges that the church or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneth, are as well to be obſerued and kepte as the canonicall ſcripture. Nother is it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defull
<pb facs="tcp:4840:51"/>
that the councell adde or put teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyes of ſcripture to his determinacyons, ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yenge that the Apoſtles and the elders dyd not ſtablyſh the fyrſt councell holden at Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem with ſcriptures. Actu. xv.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="old" type="teaching">
                  <head>The olde learnynge.</head>
                  <p>Ihon in the .iiii. Chapter of his fyrſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtell byddeth proue ſpretes whether they be of God or no, therfore it is lawfull for chriſten men to iudge the ſprete of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels: for they ſaye that the holy gooſt is author of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell. What rule ſhal we haue I pray you to proue and trye ſpretes beſyde the worde of God? This, ſeynge that is ſure, true, ſeuen tymes purged, and a candel in a darke place, ſhalbe a touch ſtone to proue &amp; to trye all learnynge of men by. Yf the holy gooſt doth rule the councelles, and the ſame ſpret of truth taught the Apoſtles eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry trueth, and yf the Apoſtles dyd preache that and geue it vnto vs, it foloweth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſtitucyons and the councels muſt agre wyth the learnynge of Chriſt and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles, that is, wyth the holy ſcripture: for the ſprete of God differeth not from hymſelfe, he is ſymple &amp; his learnyng is ſymple. But ſeynge it is openly knowen that the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels
<pb facs="tcp:4840:52"/>
haue decrees contrarye to holy ſcripture, and alſo to the holy gooſt? Who wyll for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byd vs to doute vpon ſuche conſtitucyons of councels? The Apoſtles learnynge wyll that a byſhoppe ſhulde be an huſbande of one wyfe. Ther is a councell that forbyd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth byſhoppes the vſe of holy matrimony: what authorite is here? The doctrine of Paule is the Goſpell and the lawe of God, the which ought not to be chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it doth threaten death and curſynge euen to the angelicall ſprites, yf they durſt brynge ony other Goſpell. But now yf they orden and determine thoſe thynges whiche be contrary to the ſcripture, who wyll deny but they maye erre? I haue not ſayd this to deſpyſe the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, that be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels in dede, but we ſet God aboue the councell. For we graunt accordynge to the promyſe of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueour, that Chriſt is preſent in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacyon that is gathered in the name of Chriſt, but we graunte no man power and authorite to decre &amp; orden ony thynge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of God agaynſt the ſcriptures. We receaue no man that commeth in his owne name. Ihon the .v. chapter and that ſpeaketh not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, but of his own ſelfe. Beſyde this, the ſcripture geueth no greater power
<pb facs="tcp:4840:52"/>
to a generall councel, than to .ii. or .iii. gathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red in the name of the Lorde: the which con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregacion hath authorite to exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate hym that rebelleth and is ſtubburne and an open ſynner, but it hath not authorite to make preceptes and to thruſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences that be fre. Farthermore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath prophecyed, that falſe doctores ſhuld come in the latter dayes, in the name of Chriſte, the whiche ſhall deceaue many men, ſaynge: I am Chriſte. The whyche mooſt earneſte warnynge of oure ſaueour not without a cauſe maketh vs more ware and circumſpecte, that we ſhulde not beleue euery ſprete. In dede theſe be goodly and glorious names, The church, The councel to be gathered in the name of Chriſte: but Chriſte and the Apoſtles haue warned vs, that thoſe thynges alone ſhuld not moue vs the whych dyd deſcribe theſe latter dayes, with ſo horryble colours, that it is wonder men can not perceaue theſe thynges. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian in a certayne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, where as were .lxxxvi. byſhoppes ſyttynge, taught wronge of the baptyſynge of heretikes, and for the mooſt part all the byſſhoppes of Aphrica, Numidia and Mauritania erred with hym. Yf it be ſo that the councels erre about the
<pb facs="tcp:4840:53"/>
ſacramentes of the church, who can ſafely wythout yeoperdy from hence forth beleue the councels, makyng lawes wythout ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Moeroeuer, the ſame thynges maye chaunce (we do not doute) to great and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall councels, that haue chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced vnto the particular and prouinciall councels. And ſuerly I thynke and hold that then all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhalbe more doutfull &amp; vncertayne, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the authorite of the worde doth fayle the which ought to be ſounde and vndefyled.</p>
                  <p>For the churche gaue not authorite to the word, but the worde gaue authorite to the church. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregacion beleueth the goſpell, it is ſafe, and the hereſyes which in tymes paſte were bannyſhed away and quenched, they were quenched with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde of the ſprete which is the word of God Truely hereſye is plucked vp by the roote none other waye, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the word of God &amp; wholſome learnynge. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle wyll that a biſſhop ſhuld be fenced and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed with wholſom learnyng, that he may ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me them that reſiſte and fyght a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt hym. Put the caſe that the councell dyd orden ony thynge without ſcripture, by &amp; by wyll Gerſon, and learned and honeſt men with hym ſaye: We muſt beleue more
<pb facs="tcp:4840:53"/>
the ſayenge of one man fenſed with the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorite of canonicall ſcripture, than to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the pope or the generall cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel. I paſſe ouer here the manyfeſt ſayenge of Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius in. chap. Cum venerab. De ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cep. that is to wyte: That no profe is to be admitted agaynſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, but al thyng ſhuld be holden without dout. Here vpon it foloweth, that it is not lawfull for the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to charge the congregacion with ony thynge without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the ſcriptur. And the councell of Ieruſalem decreed nothyng wythout ſcripture, boaſtynge &amp; auauncyng the holy gooſt only. For beſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos the .ix. Chapter. all other thynges had ſtrength of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, &amp; not only of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of many. For the Apoſtles &amp; ſeniors co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unded that the people ſhulde abſteyne from thoſe thynges, that were offred vp to ydols, from bloud, from ſtrangled, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fornicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The chefe and the ſum of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter was: That a man ſhuld be iuſtifyed not by the workes of the lawe, but by grace, the whiche ryghteouſneſſe of fayth, longe tyme ago was approued wyth the wytneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the lawe and the prophetes. Romano. iii. Farthermore, yf the Apoſtles dyd ſufficientlye teache by the authoryte
<pb facs="tcp:4840:54"/>
of the holy gooſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of iuſtifyenge an vnrighteous man, why dyd they that came after deuyſe &amp; ymagen other wayes of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyenge? For thoſe thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they called ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, were not neceſſary for rygteouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, but for charite. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of fallyng of the weaklynges were to be auoyded. To be ſhorte, it that the Apoſtles determyned, they myght vphold and proue by ſcripture. As concernynge it that was offred vnto ydoles, it is playne ynough: for they had it in Deutronomy that the brother ſhulde not be hurt or deſpyſed. Oure brother is deſpyſed, yf we geue hym an occaſion of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge. They dyd know that it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to eate all meates that were to be ſolde in the ſhambles, and that to the cleane all thynges are cleane, that all thynges are lawfull, but all thynges are not expedient or neceſſary, and that ther was nothynge of it ſelf commune or vncleane, but they wold not that theyr brother ſhuld be offended, for whome Chriſt dyed. Farthermor. Exod. xxxiiii. it is clearly commaunded the Iewes that they ſhuld not eate of the thynges that are offered vp, the which obſeruacion and kepynge (ſeynge that the lawe ſtocke ſo ſtyf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly as yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes hartes) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out offending
<pb facs="tcp:4840:54"/>
coulde not hayſtely be taken awaye and be contemned. Geneſis. ix. the eatynge of bloude is forbydden, the ſame alſo is forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: Leuitici. vii.xvii. and .xix. The Lorde commaunded to abſtayne from ſtrangled. Exodi. xxii. and Leuit. xxii. Whordom forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are forbydden. Deutero. v. and .xxiii. The councell had at Ieruſalem might haue ben ſtrenghtened and ſtabilyſhed with theſe places of ſcripture, the which made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes that they coulde not enioye the lyberte of Chriſt with an whole and a ſounde conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Wherfore the lawe of charite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the offendyng of oure bretheren ſhuld be auoyded. Let our councels defende theyr conſtitucions with ſcriptures, or let them commaunde thoſe thynges that be grounded vpon the ſcripture: let them haue a reſpecte to the auoydynge of offences.</p>
                  <p>Let them lay nothyng on mens neckes, but thoſe that are neceſſary, after the ſame way that they were neceſſary which were orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Apoſtles at that ſeaſon, and no man ſhall withſtande them. Therefore bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theren I beſeke yow for the mercy of God (for here we do not intreat of landemar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, or of frayle thynges, but of ſoule health) take hede and loke vpon the thynge that is
<pb facs="tcp:4840:55"/>
in all poyntes greateſt of all other, ſet all affections and troublynge of your myndes aſyde, &amp; weye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter truly and ſyncerly. Let no man ſeke thoſe thynges that be hys, but thoſe that be Ieſus Chriſtes. Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rate, ſnatche, &amp; ſpeake agaynſte hys brother. I haue a conſcience alſo, I thynke worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers and the councels. I do not deſpiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophecyes or the interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſcripture, but before al other thynges I loue and regarde holy ſcripture as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſcripture is of greater authorite (ſayeth ſaynte Auguſtyn) than all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> capacite of mans witte. Yf it had ben ſufficient vnto vs, to haue holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellyng both in witte &amp; in learninge to rule y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church or congregacion: what nede it to orden the canon of ſcripture? Yf they only make decrees of outwarde thynges, in the which we haue lyberte, why do ſome charge mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences with theſe thynges, and ſo lade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund &amp; beate in as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygently, yee a great deale more diligently ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lawes, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt holy lawe of God? As for me ſelf wittyngly &amp; with my wyll I deceaue no man, nor I wyll affyrme or hold nothyng, which is diſagreyng to the worde
<pb facs="tcp:4840:55"/>
of God, and the tatholike congregacion. So earneſtly moue I to the worde of God that yet I wold not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſion of fallyng ſhuld be geuen, the which ſpecially doth ſpringe (as thys tyme is) of the tradycions of men. And I do not ſtudy for al that, I y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myght vtterly deſtroy ceremonyes, and the ſtatutes of the fathers: but I dyd geue warnyng as it was my deuty. For ther was great difference be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene the kepyng of ceremonyes and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tradicions, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghteouſneſſe of God, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther was a certayne righteouſneſſe which muſt be earneſtly loked vpon, that we may know after what faſhyon mens conſciences ſhuld be ſtablyſhed &amp; made ſtronge agaynſt the gates of hell: and in what thynges trew penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and amendyng of our lyuyng doth ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. In the meane ſeaſon for the kepyng of peace and charite I moue &amp; exhorte to kepe the ceremonyes &amp; tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the church &amp; the fathers, where as they hynder not the ſtudy of true holyneſſe, or haue no blame or faute. Onely I moued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld not thynke, that all the ſtrength of holyneſſe dyd ſtande in deſpiſyng or kepynge of cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes. Yf ony man wyll confute it that we haue wrytten, wythout the byt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of enuy: let hym handle the matter
<pb facs="tcp:4840:56"/>
as it were w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his brother, &amp; not with hys ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye, for we be redy to confute without ſtub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bourneſſe, &amp; to be confuted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ony angre or ſtomack at al. Yf that I be thought to ony man, more hayſty and ſtyrred than the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery &amp; ſeruyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word can beare, let hym not be angry with me, but with them which ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr dyuelyſhe &amp; vngodly ouerſeynge &amp; wynkyng at abuſes &amp; errours They graunt playnly that ther be maruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous greate abuſes in the churche: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, wher as they be ſo oft warned of them, both in ſeaſon &amp; out of ſeaſon: the which they know wel ynough to be the ſede of diſcord, peſtele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of true holy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes But let vs leaue alone thys kynd of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which be not ſerue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpret, &amp; wold to god that they ſayd not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vnwyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in theyr hart: Ther is no god. Welbeloued brother I haue drawen out thys geare after a rude faſhion not gatheryng together all thynges which myght haue ben ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere) for this matter, but out of a great heap I toke a few thynges here &amp; there, but I wyl treate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe matters in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mun pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more at large. The grace of Chriſt be with the. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ The ende of the olde learnynge and new.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4840:56"/>
            <head>¶ To the Chriſten reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat thou mayeſt the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande (good reader) the arty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles of Fre wyll, Fayth, Good workes, and of Merytes, which in this preſent boke be treated vpon I ſhall here brefely ſhew what God doth and hath done for vs, and what we agayne oughte to do for his ſake as they that be thankfull of the benefites receaued of hym. And fyrſte wyll I declare the maner of iuſtificacyon, remiſſion of ſynnes, and ſaluacyon, whiche in ſcripture are all one thynge, of whom it doth come, and to how many thynges it is applyed.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt it is applyed vnto God, for Paul ſayeth Rom. viii. It is God that iuſtifyeth or maketh ryghteous. &amp;c. And Ro. iii. That he onely myght be ryghteous and the rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous maker of hym which is of the fayth on Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Secondarely it is referred vnto Chriſt Actu. iiii. ſayeth Peter: Ther is none other name geuen vnto men vnder heauen, in the which we ſhulde be ſaued. Roma. iii. ſayeth Paul: Without deſeruynge are they made ryghteous or iuſtifyed, euen by his grace thorow the redempcyon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is done by Chriſt Ieſu, whom God hath ſet forth for a mercy
<pb facs="tcp:4840:57"/>
ſeate thorow fayth in his bloude, to ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghteouſneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> auayleth before hym. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thyrdly it is applyed vnto mercy. Tit. iii. Not of workes or dedes of ryghteouſnes which we wrought, but after his mercy he ſaued vs. Roma. viii. Therfore whan God wolde ſhewe wrath, and to make his power knowen, he brought forth with great pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the veſſels of wrath, which are ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to damnacyon, that he myght declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryches of his glory on the veſſels of mercy, which he hath prepared vnto glory, whome he hath called. &amp;c. Item. i. Pet. i. Bleſſed be God and the father of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, which accordynge to his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs agayn to a lyuely hope.</p>
            <p>Fourthly it is attributed vnto his elec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon, Ephe. i. Accordynge as he hath choſen vs by hym, or euer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fundacyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde was layed, that we ſhulde be holy and with out blame before him in loue. Ioh. xv. I haue choſen you, and ordyned you, that ye go and brynge forth frute .ii. Timo. i. God hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, and called vs wyth an holy callynge not accordynge to oure dedes, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to his owne purpoſe and grace.</p>
            <p>Fyfthly it is attributed vnto grace. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe. ii. By grace are ye ſaued thorow fayth,
<pb facs="tcp:4840:57"/>
and that not of youre ſelues. Gala. i. I mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayle that ye are ſo ſoone turned from hym that hath called you in the grace of Chriſt. Tit. ii. The grace of God that bryngeth ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacyon vnto all men, hath appeared.</p>
            <p>Syxtly it is aſſygned vnto the worde. Ioh. xv. Now are ye clene becauſe of the word, which I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you. Eſa. lv. Lyke as the rayne and ſnow co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth downe from heauen, and returneth not thyther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne but watereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, maketh it frut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and grene that it maye geue corne and breade vnto the ſower: So the worde alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> commeth out of my mouth, ſhall not turne agayne voyde vnto me but ſhall accomplyſh my wyll, and proſper in the thynge whervn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to I ſhall ſende it.</p>
            <p>Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thly it is aſſcrybed vnto fayth, as Rom. iii. I ſpeake of the ryghteouſneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by fayth on Ieſus Chriſt. And Roma. iiii. Vnto hym that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth on hym that iuſtifyeth the vngodly, is fayth counted for ryghteouſneſſe. Ro. v. Becauſe that we are iuſtifyed by fayth, we haue peace with God thorow our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Eyghtly it is attribute vnto good workes as Iac. i. Ye ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of dedes a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtifyed
<pb facs="tcp:4840:58"/>
&amp; not of fayth. The places are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt (notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith only iuſtifieth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am ſure it troubleth no ſmall no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of people: and peraduenture it may aſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny euen them, which counte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues well learned. For it is a great thynge to bringe the olde and wylye foxe to a leaſe. Yee it is euen a new thynge vnto the proud Pharyſes to ſaye, that good workes are not meritorious to obtayne heauen by: for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto haue they founded and vnderpropped theyr church with nothynge ſo greatly, as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys opinion. What hath abuſed faſtynge more than thereby to obtayne heauen? For faſtynge after theyr owne choſynge, they left the true faſt, that God requyreth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth. Eſa. lviii. &amp; zach. vii. What cauſed more abuſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper of the Lorde, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vſe it that is the remembraunce of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefyt and ſacrifyce for our ſynnes, for a net &amp; hooke to gather &amp; catch mony w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>? ſayeng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a worke meritorious, &amp; a ſacrifyce for redemyng of ſynnes. Somtyme were none choſen preſtes but ſuch as were endued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch gyftes as Paul requyreth in a byſhop: now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the B. of Ro. kyngdom requyreth ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny fauterers &amp; adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> purgatory may be ſwepte and kepte clene, the which is no
<pb facs="tcp:4840:58"/>
office for ſuch Lordes as byſhops be, therfore ſyr Ihon lacklatyne ſhal ſuffiſe for that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice wel ynough, and maſſe ſhalbe made a ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice to pourge and clenſe pylgatory, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory ſhuld I haue ſayd: Lord Lord ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once oure eyen, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemy done to thy holy bloude. Now wyll I go to youre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences ye that boaſt ſo greatly of good &amp; meritorious workes: I require you by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwer, that we all ſhall geue at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great daye: Dyd Peter that was prince of the apoſtles (as ye ſaye) euer ſay naſſe for the dead ether hym ſelfe or by other? ſhew here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ony au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenticall cronicle or hys owne wrytynge. Yf ye can not, than graunt that it is an inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of youre owne, ergo a lye and a thynge that ſhall peryſh with your dayes. Yf Gods mercy ſhudle be bounde to ſende ſoules to youre purgatory, and at youre maſſynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to releaſe them, than were Chriſt no Ieſus, and God no father but a ſeruaunt of yours, and contrary to hys owne wordes &amp; doctryne. Leaue therfore youre new erroni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous doctryne, and wyth the olde teachers geue God humbly glory. What cauſed more the abuſe of honourynge of ſayntes: whyche dyenge in charite, are ioyned with vs is cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte, and therfore as true membres of one
<pb facs="tcp:4840:59"/>
body, ceaſſe not to praye with vs, ſo that worſhyppyng theyr pictures &amp; ymages, we rather blaſpheme God, which hath forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch maner of worſhyppynge, than worſhyp them. But leſte I be to tedious vnto the (good reader) therfore wyll I do my dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to expreſſe the pyth of all thys matter in fewe wordes.</p>
            <p>God the father thorow the loue that he had to hys ſonne Chriſt Ieſu, dyd caſte hys mercy vnto vs, which were ſonken into the depth of ſynne and pytied vs, &amp; of his mercy and pitye he choſe vs that we ſhulde be holy and wythout ſpotte in hys ſyghte. And to them that he choſe, he inſtilled the grace of hys ſprite, and ſent them the word of health which they receaued thorow beleuynge it: &amp; than come they to the felynge of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, and of very loue are ready to fulfyll what ſoeuer God commaundeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and loke how muche they beleue, euen ſo much they worke. And though it be true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be iuſtifyed in Chriſt before the fundaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the worlde were layed, yet is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> only knowe to God, and we haue no felynge of it vntyll fayth come. And euen as God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth downwarde, (for he thorow Chriſt had mercy on vs, and of mercy dyd choſe vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:4840:59"/>
we were, and than after we come into this world inſtilleth grace thorow his ſprete and than ſendeth vs hys worde, whiche the ſprete cauſeth vs to beleue, &amp; worketh fayth in vs, from whence all good workes flowe) eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo do we go vpward, and by my fayth do know ſurely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath ſent me hys word &amp; grace thorow his ſprete to cauſe me beleue it &amp; therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clud y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath choſen me, &amp; hath mercy vnto me thorow Chriſt hys only ſon which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mage of the inuiſible God, fyrſt begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before all creatures. Now is my dewtye agayne wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue &amp; perceaue this goodneſſe of God the father and hys ſonne Ieſus Chriſt to me warde, that I ſtonde not ſtyll and let hys grace be vacant and ydle in me: but (accordynge to the ſprete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hath poured in me, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace that is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, to vſe hys gyftes accordynge to hys wyll &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement) to procede from vertue to vertue, as from ſteppe to ſteppe alwaye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochynge oure louynge fathers kyngdome nearer and nearer, where he ſytteth &amp; ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth worlde without ende. To the which brynge vs he that wyll all mankynde to be ſaued.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>¶ Fautes eſcaped in the pryntynge.</head>
            <p>The iiii. leafe the ii. page the xii. lyne reade. Fare ye well, and praye for. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
